<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The royal presence, or, Gods tabernacle with men in a farewell sermon preached the 17. of August 1662. at Beere Regis in the county of Dorset; by that painfull and faithfull minister of the Gospel of Jesus Christ. Mr. Philip Lambe. And committed to publick view, for the instruction, support, and comfort of others.</title>
            <author>Lamb, Philip, d. 1689.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 120 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48450</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L207A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R217569</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829230</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829230</idno>
            <idno type="VID">33666</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48450)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 33666)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1991:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The royal presence, or, Gods tabernacle with men in a farewell sermon preached the 17. of August 1662. at Beere Regis in the county of Dorset; by that painfull and faithfull minister of the Gospel of Jesus Christ. Mr. Philip Lambe. And committed to publick view, for the instruction, support, and comfort of others.</title>
                  <author>Lamb, Philip, d. 1689.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[46] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>printed in the year 1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F⁴ (-F4, blank?).</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:33666:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The Royal Preſence, OR, GODS Tabernacle with MEN: IN A FAREWELL
SERMON Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the 17. of <hi>August</hi> 1662. at <hi>Beere Regis</hi> in
the County of <hi>Dorſet;</hi> By that painfull and faithfull Miniſter of
the Goſpel of JESUS CHRIST.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>PHILIP LAMBE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And committed to publick view, for the Inſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Support,
and comfort of others.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Iſa. 30.20.</bibl> 
               <p>Though the Lord give you the bread of adverſity, and the water
of affliction, yet ſhall not thy Teachers be remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved into a corner <hi>any
more,</hi> but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>John 10.27.</bibl> 
               <p>My ſheep hear my voice, and I know them, and they follow
me.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>2 Epiſt. John ver. 9.</bibl> 
               <p>Whoſoever tranſgreſſeth, and abideth not in the doctrine
of Chriſt, hath not God: he that abideth in the doctrine of Chriſt, he hath
both the Father and the Son.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 John 2.5.</bibl> 
               <p>Whoſo keepeth his word, in him verily is the Love of God
perfected.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed in the Year 1662.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:33666:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:33666:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WEe the Inhabitants of <hi>Beere</hi> and <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone</hi> in
the County of <hi>Dorſet,</hi> who have lived under the Rich Droppings,
Plentiful Soul-ſearching, Enlivening and Refreſhing Dews of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, which
<hi>HE</hi> who promiſed to be as the Dew unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.5.</note> hath conveyed to us, by one of his Eminent and
Faithful Meſſengers of the Goſpel of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> for many years amongſt us hath
endeavoured (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks of himſelf) to be pure from the blood
of all men, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare <hi>All,</hi> and <hi>Onely</hi> the Counſels of
God:<note place="margin">Acts 20.26,27.</note> And was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in Seaſon,
and out of Seaſon, diligent in the work of the Lord, according as the ſame
Apoſtle doth ſtrictly exhort unto, taking heed to himſelf, and to the
flock, over the which the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> made him
<hi>Overſeer;</hi>
               <note place="margin">See 2 Tim. 4.1,2.</note> And of whom we
can truly ſay, (and to which many can bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) that he was, and
is, an example of the Believers, in Word, in Converſation, in Charity, in
Spirit, in Faith, in Purity.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12.</note> His Life and
Converſation adorns his Profeſsion, and Doctrine; And having received much
Benefit and Comfort by his Miniſtry, have endeavoured to Communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate to
thee, ſome of thoſe Spiritual advantages, and Conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, we have
enjoyed, through the Bleſsing of God, upon his diligent and faithful Labours,
in his last publick Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe, which he deliverod amongst us; Wiſhing the
like Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit and Comfort to thee, and more alſo, than we have had. Becauſe
of our <hi>Non-improvement</hi> of ſuch choice Mercies, and rich Priviledges,
which we have ſufficient cauſe to be Humbled for; And continually to lament
that we are now deprived of them, by his removal from us.</p>
            <p>And had this following diſcourſe been ſet ſorth to
pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <pb facs="tcp:33666:3"/>view by the Author himſelf (whoſe Modeſty would
con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal his worthy Labours) It would have been more large and perfect, and
ſo render'd more acceptable. We muſt there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore deſire thee (Chriſtian
Reader) with a charitable Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to cover over verbal or literal
miſtakes, and in Love to Correct with thy pen, what may be found amiſſe
by thee, in this following Treatiſe, wherein are contained, <hi>Things of the
moſt weighty concernment,</hi> and which are Exceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing uſeful at all time,
for Edification and Inſtruction to All; and will Adminiſter matter of
ſufficient Comfort under any Condition to them that have the Special Abode of
God and Christ with them.</p>
            <p>The Lord Jeſus Chriſt by his Spirit; lead thee into all
Truth.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>So Prayes Thine in Chriſt.</signed>
            </closer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>VINCENTI DABITUR.</q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:33666:3"/>
            <head>The Royal Preſence, OR Gods Tabernacle with Men.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>JOHN XIV. XXIII.</bibl> 
                  <p>Jeſus anſwered, and ſaid unto him; If a man love me, he
will keep my words; and my Father will love him, and we will come unto him, and
make our Abode with him.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Departure of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> unto his Father, from
whoſe boſome he came into the World, was very ſadly reſented by his
Diſciples; whoſe mixt paſſions produce a very great diſturbance, and
trouble upon their Spirits.</p>
            <p>The inward Anxiety, and unconcealed grief of the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples,
move the Bowels of their more affectionate Lord, to pitty their caſe, and
provide for their relief, and gives them inſtructions how to expreſſe
their love unto him in his abſence, not ſo much in carrying bluber'd eyes,
and heavy hearts, as by remembring, and obſerving the Councels, and
Inſtructions that he had give to them, while he was preſent with them; So
that this whole Chapter is fill'd up with Counſels, and Comforts, Directions,
and Conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Directions and Counſels, eſpecially in the
1, 13, 15. <hi>verſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1 Faith.</note>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To the
exerciſe of Faith, <hi>verſe</hi> 1. <hi>Ye believe in God, believe alſo
in me.</hi> And this is the life, even a life of Faith, which we muſt live,
till we come to enjoyment <pb facs="tcp:33666:4"/>of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by which we fetch
comforts in all troubles, and ſtrength againſt all tentations from
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. Prayer.</note>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To the duty
of Prayer, <hi>verſ.</hi> 13. which is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per duty of an afflicted
State, as <hi>Jam.</hi> 5.13. <hi>Is any afflicted? let hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> pray.</hi> By prayer the Soul empties his complaints
into <hi>Gods</hi> boſome, and finds eaſe, by telling him of all the
trouble and grief that attends his ſtate; <hi>Prayer</hi> hath that Divine
excellency, that like a Heavenly Charm, it ſpeaks away trouble, and ſpeaks
in comfort; as 'tis ſaid of <hi>Hannah</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 1.18. <hi>She
prayed, and went away, and did eat, and her Countenance was no more ſad;</hi>
And thus our prayers alwayes ſpeed, when they be made by the help of the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> and offered up to <hi>God</hi> in the name of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> 13, 14. verſes. <hi>Whatſoever you ſhall ask the
Father in my name, that you ſhall receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</note>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To
Obedience, in the 15 <hi>verſ.</hi> to do the work committed to them; <hi>If
yee love me, keep my Commandements.</hi> You cannot better expreſſe your
love to me, then in keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my words; Nor is there a more certain way for men
to find comfort, than this; 
<note place="margin">3 Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 17.</note> 
               <hi>by keeping his Commands,</hi> for then, though they
cannot enjoy his <hi>perſon,</hi> yet they ſhall not miſſe his
<hi>promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Conſolations which he gives them in the 2
<hi>verſ. &amp;c.</hi> the 16 <hi>verſ. &amp;c.</hi> and 23 <hi>verſ.
&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">1. The place to which he
goes.</note>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> In the 2, 3, 4, <hi>verſes, &amp;c.</hi> From
the place whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was going, <hi>To his Father, and their Father, his Home,
and their Home;</hi> whence he did intend to come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain to them. So that his
going from them, was but a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, or withdrawing for a time, untill he
came, for in the 3 <hi>verſ. I will come again, and receive you to my
ſelf,</hi> rendred in the <hi>Greek.</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">Gr.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentenſe.</note> I
come again, in the preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſe, to intimate the certainty of his coming to
them a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, as if he were already come; which in the 28 <hi>verſ.</hi> of
this Chapter, <hi>Chriſt</hi> tells them, ſhould be matter of great Joy to
them. <hi>If yee loved me, yee would rejoyce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I ſaid, I go unto
the Father.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his Spirit the
Comforter.</note>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> From the 16 <hi>v.</hi> The promiſe of
the <hi>Spirit,</hi> which ſhall ſupply his abſence, ſuch a
<hi>Spirit,</hi> as ſhall teach them, comfort them, and be
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>ead of all to them, give them
ſuch Joy, Courage, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, as
the world can neither <pb facs="tcp:33666:4"/>give, nor take away, 27 <hi>verſ. Peace I
leave with you, my peace I give unto you,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">The abode of God and Chriſt with
them.</note>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> In the 23. <hi>verſe,</hi> in the Text, <hi>We
will come, and makeour abode with him, while you keep my words;</hi> which is
the great promiſe here.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If a man love me, he will keep my words, and my Father will
love him, and we will come unto him, and make our abode with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The words of the Text</hi> are an anſwer to the queſtion
of <hi>Judas,</hi> (not <hi>Iſcariot</hi>) <hi>Lord how is it, that thou wilt
manifeſt thy ſelf unto us, and not unto the world? Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
gives the anſwer. <hi>If a man love me, he will keep my words,</hi> &amp;c.
To him the promiſe is made, That the <hi>Father</hi> will love him, They love
him that keep his words, and to theſe he hath ſaid, <hi>he will manifeſt
his love to them, and make his abode with them;</hi> In which words there are
three parts conſiderable.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Parts of the Text. 3.</note>
               <hi>First,</hi> A
Suppoſition. If a man love me, he <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> A Poſition. Which is the effect of that love.
<hi>He will keep my words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> A Promiſe. Which is twofold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Of the <hi>Fathers</hi> love. <hi>My Father will
love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Co-habitation of the <hi>Father and
Son</hi> with ſuch a perſon. <hi>We will come unto him, and make our abode
with him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Obſervations</hi> that I intend to inſiſt upon, are
two;</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>2</label> Firſt, <hi>That it is the duty
and ſpecial property of them that love</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>in
ſincerity, to keep the words of</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>That God and Chriſt will make their abode with
them that keep his words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Of the firſt of theſe,</hi> That it is the duty
and ſpecial property of them that love <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in
ſincerity, to keep the words of <hi>Christ.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>If any man love me, he will keep my words, he will do my will,
walk in my wayes, treaſure up my truths and Counſells.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This Doctrine</hi> requires three things to be ſpoken to in
their order.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>muſt be truly
loved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, What it is to keep his words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Why it is both the duty and property of them that
love him, to keep his words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:5"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
muſt be truly loved; there is ſuch an indiſpenſible neceſſity of
this, that the Apoſtle ſayes 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.22. <hi>If any man love not
the Lord Jeſus, let him be</hi> Anathema Maranatha, <hi>let him be
curſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But becauſe every one pretends highly to love <hi>Jeſus
Christ,</hi> and but few that love him indeed, I ſhall ſhew two things more
briefly;</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Who he is that truly loves him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Why we ſhould all truly love him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Who he is that truly loves
<hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He truly loves <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who
upon the diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and tender of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> in the Goſpel,
as <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and <hi>Prophet,</hi> can willingly deny all for
him; as the Merchant, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.45.46. ſold all that he had for the
goodly Pearl. And ſo <hi>Paul, Phil.</hi> 3.8. <hi>accounts all Dung,</hi>
his parts, his righteouſneſs by the Law, his greateſt excellencies; He
loves Chriſt in <hi>Deed,</hi> and not in <hi>Shew</hi> only, who can leave
the world, his deareſt luſts, his beſt righteouſneſs for
<hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is a true conjugal love, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45.10. <hi>Hearken
O daughter, and confider, and encline thine ear, forget alſo thine own
people,</hi> &amp;c. When <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſees that we have ſuch a love
to him, that we will part with all for him, then he ſees a beauty in us that
delights him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He truly loves <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> who
having received him, will rather loſe all, than part with him again; who
ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> better than his beſt things, as he
ſayes in <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.37. <hi>He that loves Father or Mother more than
me, is not worthy of me,</hi> &amp;c. therefore ſayes the Spouſe,
<hi>Cant.</hi> 8.6. <hi>Set me as a ſeal upon thine heart, as a ſeal upon
thine arm: let me be ſo united to thee, that I may never be ſever'd from
thee.</hi> It is a very hard leſſon, and an irkſom duty for the beſt of
men, to part with friends, liberty, peace, life; all theſe, or either of
theſe ſweet mercies; but to part with <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nothing can
perſwade, or enforce the Soul that truly loves him; that's a thought more
cruel than the Grave, witneſs the holy <hi>Martyrs,</hi> a whole cloud of
witneſſes; that notable and eminent <hi>Galeacius,</hi> Marqueſs of
<hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He that truly loves <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
takes abundance of delight in Communion with him. No <hi>pleaſure</hi> like
the kiſſes of his mouth, no <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> like that of his
boſom, all his <pb facs="tcp:33666:5"/>wayes are peace, and his paths
pleaſantneſſe; <hi>Chriſt</hi> makes every condition Comfortable, there
is no comfort of life, but in that little enjoyment of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that
the Soul hath in his life, 'tis <hi>Communion</hi> with <hi>Chriſt,
converſe</hi> with him, that is all my <hi>comfort</hi> and
<hi>pleaſure</hi> in the world. O how doth the Spouſe take care that he be
not diſturbed, in <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.7. <hi>I charge you, O yee daughters of
Jeruſalem, by the Roes, and by the Hinds of the field, that ye ſtirr not
up, nor awake my Love, till he pleaſe.</hi> The words are an alluſion, to
one that would not have her Friend diſturbed, and ſpeaks to her
Compani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and charges them by all that is dear and pleaſant to them, not
to break the reſt of her <hi>beſt Beloved,</hi> and ſhews the wonderful
delight the Soul takes in Communion with <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and the
ſpecial care that it alwayes hath, that no Tentation break in, nor corruption
break out, to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt that ſweet Communion, or occaſion
<hi>Chriſts</hi> depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, who will not for any profit, commit any ſin,
or cauſe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to depart from him.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, He that truly loves <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> having
loſt the ſight of him, is never ſatisfied, till he come to the
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enjoyment of him, is alwayes at loſſe, and is never quiet, till he
enters into a freſh acquaintance and communion with him, as in that of
<hi>Joſeph</hi> and <hi>Mary,</hi> they having loſt their Son, went
ſeeking till they found him; So <hi>Cant.</hi> 3.1,2,3. <hi>&amp;c. By night
on my Bed, I ſought him whom my Soul loveth, I ſought him, but I found him
not, I will riſe now and go about the City, in the Streets, and in the broad
wayes,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>I ſaid to the Watchmen, Saw ye him whom my Soul
loveth? &amp;c.</hi> By all which, is expreſſed the ſedulous care and
induſtry of a living Soul ſeeking after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>By night in her bed.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt hath her
bed thoughts, <hi>(i.)</hi> in her Cloſet and private duties, of Prayer,
ſerious Meditations, Spiritual Ejaculations, and ſecret ſelf
Examinations; in all theſe the Soul enquires. As one that loves the World, by
night his Meditation is of the World; ſo the man of pleaſures, and honours,
is purſuing his luſts in the night ſeaſon; <hi>The wicked man is
contriving miſchief up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his bed.</hi> So the Soul that loves
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> his thoughts are ſtill at work after Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>I will riſe now and go about the City, &amp;c.
(i.)</hi> 
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:6"/>I will betake my ſelf to all publick Ordinances, and
ſhew more zeal and life in my duties, and in theſe will I make enquiry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, I asked the watch-men, (i.)</hi> the Miniſters of
the Goſpel, which are or ſhould be as <hi>faithful watch-men,</hi> that
watch for our Souls, and be able <hi>to ſpeak a word in ſeaſon,
&amp;c.</hi> So nothing will ſatisfie the Soul that truly loves Chriſt
without him; and no means ſhall be neglected till ſhe enjoy Him.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why muſt he be
thus beloved?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe
he is lovely, <hi>altogether lovely.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Lovely in his <hi>life,</hi> obſerving all the
will of <hi>God;</hi> there was a wonderful beauty upon him, if we behold, and
can underſtand, that hidden glory of an untainted Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and exact
conformity to the will of <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Lovely in his <hi>death,</hi> never more lovely
and amiable to the believing Sinner, then when he was moſt deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>picable in
the eyes of Rebellious Sinners. O then, he appears moſt beautiful and
deſireable, when he hangs on the Croſſe, there making our Peace,
procuring our Pardon, obtaining Life and Glory for us, by that ſhameful
death.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Lovely in all his <hi>Graces,</hi> each Grace a
match<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe Jewel. Rocks of Diamonds, Mountains of Pearl, not worthy to be
mentioned with the leaſt of his Excellencies; If he put but a little of this
Grace upon any Soul, though he be never ſo vile, cloath'd with corruption; as
in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. from the 9. to the 16 <hi>verſ. yet may be made
beautiful by his Comelineſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Lovely in all his <hi>Ordinances,</hi> in which
the more immediate ſight the Soul hath of him, the more he is taken with his
Beauty; No wonder he is call'd in <hi>Hag.</hi> 2.7. <hi>the deſire of all
Nations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe
of his deſerving love; <hi>we loved him, becauſe he firſt loved
us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider in his love, theſe four particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He laid down his life for us, <hi>ſuch a Love,
will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve love, and life too;</hi> Joh. 15.13. <hi>Greater Love, hath no
man, then this, that a man lay down his life for his friend.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He lives now in Heaven for us, 7 <hi>Heb.</hi>
25. <hi>He ever liveth, to make interceſſion for them.</hi> He is there 
<pb facs="tcp:33666:6"/>minding our neceſſities, agitating our affairs; by his
ſitting there, we have Liberty of comming thither; by his ſitting there in
glory, we have our ſtanding here in Grace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He accounts that as done to himſelf, that is
done to them, that are his, <hi>Zach.</hi> 2.8. <hi>He that toucheth you,
toucheth the Apple of his eye, and</hi> Mat. 10.40,41,42. &amp;c. <hi>He that
receiveth you, receiveth me,</hi> and ſo he ſaid to <hi>Saul,</hi> Acts
9.4. <hi>why perſecuteſt thou me?</hi> when he was with Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
from the <hi>High Prieſt,</hi> dragging the poor Profeſſors of
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to the Priſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He longs to have us with him. <hi>Joh.</hi>
17.24. <hi>Father I will that where I am, there they may be alſo, to behold
my Glory.</hi> He is not <hi>(q. d.)</hi> ſatisfied without their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny;
and is alwayes imparting his moſt ſecret Counſels to them, <hi>Joh.</hi>
15.16. <hi>Henceforth I call you not Servants, for the Servant knoweth not what
his Lord doth, but I have cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led you Friends, for all things that I have heard
of my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, I have made known unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe
otherwiſe we ſhall not regard his words; which is intimated in the Text,
<hi>If we love him, we ſhall keep his Words,</hi> but if we love him not, we
will not keep his Words; It is want of love to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> that is the
cauſe of the abounding of every ſin, for if we did love him, we ſhould
keep his Commands, which is the ſecond particular.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> What is it to keep
the words of <hi>Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> There is <hi>a Natural and Mental keeping of the
words of Christ;</hi> and ſo we muſt keep them, that is, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member his
Words, his promiſes, Counſels, and Appointments.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Memory is mans Storehouſe, or Cabinet, that ſhould be kept
Sacred for the Truths of <hi>Chriſt;</hi> So the Diſciples kept the word of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> when they remembred his ſayings; and <hi>David</hi>
Pſal. 119.93. <hi>J will never forget thy Precepts, for by them thou haſt
quickned me,</hi> (i.) <hi>I will keep thy Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts;</hi> for what we forget,
we loſe, and what we remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, we keep; And thus, as Friends take pleaſure
to look ſometimes on the Love-tokens of their abſent Friends. So may we
have ſingular comfort and refreſhment, to ſee the Heart of Chriſt in
the Counſels, Promiſes, and Appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments left with us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:7"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is an <hi>Evangelical and
Practical keeping of the words of Chriſt.</hi> When we do believe promiſes,
and obey commands; <hi>Promiſes not believed, and Precepts not obey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, are
as water ſpilt on the earth, beſides the veſſel that ſhould receive
it, Heb.</hi> 4.2. but when they are believed, <hi>they be as liquor put into
the veſſel for its proper uſe.</hi> Hence ſaies <hi>Chriſt,</hi> Luke
11.28. <hi>Bleſſed are they that hear the word of God and keep it.</hi>
Then we keep the words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his promiſes,
obſerve his precepts in all our converſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and walk by his appointments
and inſtitutions in all our duties.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Why 'tis their property and duty that love
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> to keep his words.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe
<hi>true love is comprehenſive;</hi> He that love Chriſt truly loves all
that is his; <hi>He that loves him that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat, loves him alſo that is
begotten:</hi> The nearer any thing is to Chriſt, the better it is beloved;
and then we love the word when we keep it, as a ſpecial pledge of his love;
<hi>To have his word, and a heart to keep it, is a double bleſſing;</hi>
and indeed, ſuch a gift as the word of <hi>Christ</hi> is, is worthy to be
loved for it ſelf, and kept for the givers ſake.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe
<hi>true love is Operative,</hi> 'tis the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of Goſpel obedience, 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 5.14. <hi>The love of Chriſt conſtraineth us.</hi> Where
there is the diſpoſition of a Son, there will be obedience to the Fathers
commands; ſo where there is a ſpiritual love to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> it will
ſet the ſoul on work, and quicken it to keep the words of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> as is ſaid of Faith, <hi>Shew me thy Faith by thy
works.</hi> So ſhew thy love to <hi>Chriſt</hi> by thy works; as Faith
without works is dead, ſo is love without obedience.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſon. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe
<hi>keeping the words of Chriſt gives the cleareſt and ſureſt
teſtimony of the truth of our love to Jeſus Christ. Probatio
delectationis eſt exhibitio operis;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Greg. Hom.</note>
Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is the moſt lively teſtification of love, as <hi>Chriſt</hi>
ſaid to <hi>Peter, Loveſt thou me?</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſhew it in this, in
doing thy du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; Feed my ſheep.</hi> So Chriſt tells us in the Text,
<hi>Where the fire of love is in the breaſt, there the flame of duty and
ſervice is in the hands.</hi> Joh, 15.14. <hi>Ye are my friends, if ye do
what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever I command you.</hi> In the 1 Joh. 5.3. <hi>In this is the love of
God, that we keep his Commandments.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33666:7"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Uſe</hi> 1.
For Exhortation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To a mental keeping of the words of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that word, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.1. <hi>We ought
therefore to give the more diligent heed, to the things which we have received,
leſt at any time we let them ſlip.</hi> And that we may not forget, but
keep in our memories the words of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt conſider,</hi> That all the promiſes and
counſells, which <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath made known to us, are not
only for preſent, but for future uſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42.23. <hi>Hearken
and hear for the time to come.</hi> We ſhould hear as if we were to hear no
more. The Cordial which hath ſome time revived us, muſt not be laid
aſide, leſt for want of it another time, we faint quite a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. The reaſon
why they were ready to faint under af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. was,
<hi>becauſe they had forgotten the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation, which ſpeaketh to them as
to Sons.</hi> For this cauſe <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> often bids his
Diſciples <hi>remember the word he had ſpoken to them,</hi> and knowing
their frailty, promiſes his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.26. and that (ſayes
he) <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>ſhall bring to your
remembrance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly conſider,</hi> Not to remember the words of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> is a ſad ſign of our diſ-eſteem of <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt.</hi> We uſually remember Precepts, Counſels, and Sayings,
according to the authority which the perſon hath with us, from whence they
come. It is a very great diſhonour to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when we
ſhall caſt his words behind our backs. Did we honour <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt</hi> as our <hi>King, Lord, and Lawgiver,</hi> we ſhould be more
careful to remember what he hath ſpoken to us. We often blame our
<hi>heads,</hi> as if the fault lay only there, that we do not remember the
words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> when indeed the fault lies moſt in the
<hi>hearts,</hi> that we have not more love and eſteem of <hi>Chriſt</hi>
there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The time will come, when we ſhall dearly
repent every truth forgotten, that we did not endeavour <hi>to ſeal
in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction upon our hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> When <hi>God</hi> ſhall with-hold
inſtruction from us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have refuſed it; the time may come, when
as <hi>Amos</hi> 8.12. <hi>Men ſhall run to and fro, and ſeek the word of
the Lord, and ſhall not find it;</hi> and then we ſhall ſee the worth of
the word, that now we <hi>prize not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When <hi>God</hi> ſhall call us to an account
for all the <pb facs="tcp:33666:8"/>Sermons, and Inſtructions we have received, as he
will cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly do; though we forget, yet he will remember, and he will ask how
we have kept, and improved the Word he hath ſpoken to us.</p>
            <p>To help us in keeping, or remembring the words of
<hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Directions. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let your
hearts be affected with the worth and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency of the word, that it is more
precious than Gold or Silver: and then we ſhall keep it as choice treaſure.
That which a man prizeth, he will keep in ſafe cuſtody, and have often in
his eyes, as <hi>David</hi> ſayes of the word, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.97. <hi>O
how I love thy Law, it is my meditation all the day long.</hi> It a man account
the word as his treaſure, he will not forget it, as <hi>Jerem.</hi> 2.32.
<hi>Can a Maid forget her Ornaments, or a Bride her Attires?</hi> This they
forget not; Yet becauſe we account not the word as excellent and
neceſſary as theſe, therefore it follows, <hi>Yet my people have
forgotten me dayes without number.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly.</hi> Apply every word of <hi>Chriſt</hi> to your
own ſouls, though men will not keep what is anothers, yet uſually they keep
what is their own; while men carve away the word to others, as if it concern'd
them not, 'tis no marvel if they keep it not, but if we accounted every word as
ſpoken to us, and our portion, we ſhould hear and keep it. Men re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
the news which concerns themſelves. We ſhould hear <hi>Chriſt</hi>
ſpeaking, as <hi>Job</hi> 5.27. <hi>Hear thou this, know it for thy
good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Meditate often upon what you have received, as
<hi>Mary pondered the ſayings</hi> which ſhe heard, <hi>in her heart</hi>
The way to keep any thing ſafe, is to have a conſtant eye upon it.
Meditation is the Souls ſerious retiring into it ſelf, to take a view of
all that of <hi>God,</hi> that is laid up within it ſelf.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Haſten to do all that you have heard and
learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.60. It is ſaid by <hi>David, I made haſt and
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed not the time to keep his Commandments.</hi> A man will not eaſily
forget his Trade; ſo if we daily obey commands, and believe promiſes, we
cannot eaſily forget the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands and promiſes given to us: which laſt
direction leads to the ſecond exhortation.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:33666:8"/>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It
may exhort us to keep the words of <hi>Chriſt</hi> with an Evangelical and
Practical keeping. Keep the word as a man keeps his Rule or the Souldier keeps
his Weapon; let not the word depart from thee, and do not thou depart from it,
by forſaking the appointments and commands of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> conſider, That if we do not keep the words of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> by obeying, and a ſuitable walking, we do but in vain
pretend love to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> as they that had no more of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> but to call him Lord, (<hi>Mat.</hi> 7.21.) <hi>Not every
one that ſaith unto me, Lord, Lord, ſhall enter into the Kingdom of
Heaven,</hi> &amp;c. So, not every one that ſayes he loves me, but he that
doth my word, he is my friend.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> conſider what a ſin it is to pretend love
to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and not ſo truly to love him, as to keep his words;
'tis Hypocriſie; they be <hi>Chriſt</hi>'s falſe friends, an open enemy
is leſs dangerous than they, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.31. <hi>They hear thy words,
but they will not do them, their heart goes after their covetouſneſs;</hi>
They be falſe to themſelves, and delude their own ſouls with a bare
profeſſion and hearing, <hi>Jam.</hi> 1.22. <hi>Be doers of the word, and
not hearers only, deceiving your own ſouls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> conſider what judgement they incurre, and who
can tell how great it is? 'tis call'd a beating with more ſtripes, when the
leaſt ſtripe from that hand can break the loynes, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.47.
<hi>He that knoweth his Maſters will, and doth it not, ſhall be beaten with
many ſtripes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly</hi> conſider, This is the cleareſt evidence of
our intereſt in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> of his love to us, <hi>that we keep his
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments.</hi> By this we know that we have him as our <hi>Chriſt,</hi>
when we do not only love him as a <hi>Jeſus,</hi> a Saviour, but obey him as
a <hi>Lord,</hi> and follow his Law. When <hi>God</hi> ſhall write his Law in
our hearts, Is not this an evidence that <hi>Chriſt</hi> is ours?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Great and many are the encouragements which he
hath promiſed to them that keep his words. There be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny bleſſings in
the word, but they only have the bleſſings for theirs, who keep his word,
<hi>Jam.</hi> 1.15. <hi>Whoſo looketh into the perfect Law of Liberty, and
continueth therein, he being not a forgetful hearer, but a doer of the work,
this man ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <pb facs="tcp:33666:9"/>in his deed;</hi> he ſhall ask
what he will, and have it, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.7. <hi>If you abide in me, and my
words abide in you, ask what you will, and it ſhall be done unto
you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>
               </label> That we may do the words of
<hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let it be the aim and intentions of our ſouls,
when we come to hear, to turn hearing into doing. Say as <hi>Paul</hi> did,
<hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. <hi>Lord what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> and
<hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius, Acts</hi> 10.33. <hi>Now therefore are we all here preſent
be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God, to hear all things that are commanded thee of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Beg of <hi>God</hi> to give you ſuch a heart,
that you may not only ſay, as the people in a good humour, once to
<hi>Moſes; All that thou ſhalt ſpeak unto us, that will we obſerve and
do;</hi> but find your hearts ſuch as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 5.29. <hi>O that
there were ſuch an heart in them, that they would fear me, and keep all my
Commandments always,</hi> &amp;c. It is he by whom the word is made (as
<hi>James</hi> hath it)<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Jam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1.
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. engraffed.</note>
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>A fruit-bearing word.</hi>
Begin all your hearing with prayers, and conclude them with prayers, becauſe
'tis of the greateſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernment.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> A uſe of
comfort.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> If we keep this word, the word will keep us. It
will keep us in the worſt of times, yea at all times, <hi>Pro.</hi> 6.22.
<hi>When thou goeſt, it ſhall lead thee; when thou ſleepeſt it ſhall
keep thee; and when thou awakeſt, it ſhall talk with thee.</hi> If you keep
his Commands, his Commands will keep you; If you keep his Promiſes, his
Promiſes will bring you to Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> If we keep his word, we ſhall not want
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent comforts. The preſent gratuities which we have from
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould be enough to encourage us, if there were no future
reward, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 19. <hi>In keeping of them there is great
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. verſe.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath promiſed a
bleſſedneſs to ſuch perſons; they be a bleſſed people,
<hi>Rev.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Bleſſed is he that readeth, and they that hear the
words of this Prophecy, and keep thoſe things which are written therein;</hi>
and ſo in <hi>Luke</hi> 11.28. <hi>Bleſſed are they,</hi> &amp;c. and
with the beſt of bleſſings doth be crown them in the Text, <hi>My Father
will love him, and we will come to him, and will make our abode with him;</hi>
which is the ſecond obſervation.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:9"/> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Obſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>God and Chriſt will make
their abode with them that keep his word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In which <hi>Obſervation,</hi> we ſhall take notice of theſe
three particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> How <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> do make
their abode with them that keep his word.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Why <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> will
make their abode with ſuch.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What an excellent bleſſing it is to have
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> abiding with us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> How <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> do make
their abode with them that keep his word; in which theſe three particulars
muſt be ſhown.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. How <hi>God</hi> abides with his People.</item>
               <item> 2. How <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> abides with them.</item>
               <item> 3. How both <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> will make
their abode with them that keep his word.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> How <hi>God,</hi> the firſt Perſon in the
<hi>Trinity,</hi> is ſaid to make his abode with them that keep his word.</p>
            <p>And this will be two wayes ſeen.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is not here to be underſtood of his common
or general preſence, as he is the infinite <hi>God,</hi> and being
<hi>Omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent,</hi> fills Heaven and Earth: for ſo he abides with all
the works of his hands; yea, ſo he is with them that fear him not.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is here properly underſtood of
<hi>Gods</hi> abode by way of ſpecial preſence, as he is a gracious
<hi>Father;</hi> there fore <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> doth firſt expreſs
the <hi>Fathers</hi> love, and then his abode, as the product and fruit of his
love, <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will love him, and we will come unto him,</hi> &amp;c. He
will come and abide with his, as <hi>a God in Covenant</hi> with them,
therefore hath he put it into a promiſe, in the 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>I
will dwell in them, and walk in them, and I will be their God, and they ſhall
be my people.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> How <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> will make his
abode with them that keep his word? which will be ſhown alſo,
<hi>Firſt,</hi> Negatively. <hi>Secondly,</hi> Affirmatively.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt Negatively,</hi> It is not to be underſtood of a
carnal or corporeal preſence of <hi>Chriſt</hi> (as the Papiſt imagine)
as if the fleſh of <hi>Chriſt</hi> could be in all places, <hi>whom the
Heavens muſt <pb facs="tcp:33666:10"/>contain till the time of reſtitution of all
things:</hi> for ſaies the Apoſtle, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.16. acknowledging,
<hi>If he had known Chriſt after the fleſh, yet ſo, he knows him no
more.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Affirmatively,</hi> He makes abode with his people
after a ſpiritual manner, <hi>God the Father</hi> makes his abode with his
Servants, as a Father to them; <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> abides with them, as
the Head of his Church, as it is in <hi>Ephe.</hi> 5.23. <hi>He is the Head of
his Church, and the Saviour of his Body. God</hi> abides with us in
<hi>Chriſt, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> abides with us by his <hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Corn
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lap.</note>A learned Author
ſhews four ways of <hi>Chriſts</hi> abode with Believers.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Politicè ut Rex in Regno,</hi> As a King in his
Kingdom; and ſo he gives Laws as the only Head, and King of his Church:
protects them, and order all their affairs.</item>
               <item> 2. <hi>Oeconomicè, ut Puter in Dome,</hi> As a Father
in his Houſe; and ſo he takes care, and makes proviſion for his people,
as a Father doth for his Family.</item>
               <item> 3. <hi>Ethicè, ut ratio in homine,</hi> As reaſon
in a man, which is the light that directs man in all his actions; ſo
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects and leads his people.</item>
               <item> 4. <hi>Phiſice, us Anima in Corpore,</hi> As the Soul in
the Body, which animates and acts the whole man, without which the Body is a
dead, and liveleſs Trunck; ſo <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> doth quicken our
ſoules, by whom we have ſpiritual life.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And that he is the Head of his <hi>Church,</hi> and thus abides
with them,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First</hi> conſider, He hath all grace and life in him;
<hi>John</hi> 5.26. <hi>As the Father hath life in himſelf, ſo hath he
given to the Son, to have life in himſelf;</hi> therefore the
<hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaies, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.9. <hi>With thee is the Well
of life, and in thy light, ſhall we ſee light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> From him is all grace and life conveyed out
un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us, <hi>John</hi> 1.16. <hi>of his fulneſs have we all received, and
grace for grace.</hi> Yea, whatſoever we receive from the <hi>Spirit</hi> of
<hi>God,</hi> we have from him originally, as in <hi>John</hi> 16.15. <hi>For
he ſhall take of mine and ſhew it unto you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> How <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> are both
ſaid to make their abode with them that keep his word. And this I ſhall
ſhew to be three wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:10"/>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> by their ſpecial
<hi>Providence</hi> and <hi>Inſpection with them,</hi> and ſo we may ſee
them in ſeveral Scriptures, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biding with them, as in <hi>Zach.</hi>
1.8,9,10. <hi>verſes, there's Jeſus Chriſt among the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> which repreſent the
<hi>Church,</hi> and <hi>in Revel.</hi> 1.13. <hi>He is there in the midſt of
his Golden Candleſticks,</hi> and <hi>David</hi> tells us of his experience
of <hi>Gods</hi> preſence with him, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.23. <hi>I am
continually with thee, thou upholdeſt me with thy right hand,</hi> and the
Apoſtle <hi>Paul,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.17. <hi>The Lord stood by me;</hi>
indeed the eyes of the <hi>Lord</hi> are upon the Righteous, and he hath
ſaid, he will not leave them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They make their abode with them in the
<hi>Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel Ordinances,</hi> where theſe be
continued in their power and purity, there <hi>the Tabernacle of God is among
men,</hi> and when theſe are taken away, <hi>I-chabod,</hi> the Glory is
departed; We may ſay <hi>God</hi> hath forſaken us. As the <hi>Ark</hi> was
a Tipe, and Token of <hi>God;</hi> ſpecial preſence with the <hi>Jews,</hi>
ſo the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel Ordinances,</hi> are a ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal,
Token of <hi>Gods</hi> abode with us, for in theſe we may ſee him, in
theſe, we may enjoy him, by theſe, we may be made like to him, as in the 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 3.18. <hi>But we all with open face, behold as in a Glaſſe
the Glory of God, and are changed into the ſame Image, from Glory to Glory,
even as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> They make their abode with them in the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> which proceeds from the <hi>Father,</hi> and the <hi>Son;</hi>
So they may both be ſaid truly to abide with us, while we have the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> the Comforter, which proceeds from the <hi>Father,</hi> and
the <hi>Son,</hi> as a pledge of their Love, <hi>Joh.</hi> 15.20. <hi>When the
Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forter is come, whom I will ſend unto you, from the Father, I will ſend
him ſayes Chriſt, even the Spirit of truth,</hi> which
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which proceeds from the
<hi>Father,</hi> there is an <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a
<hi>Proceſſion</hi> of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> from the <hi>Father,</hi>
and the <hi>Son,</hi> to the <hi>People</hi> that keep his word; and thus
Believers are ſaid to hold fellowſhip with the <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and the
<hi>Son,</hi> in the 1 <hi>Epiſt.</hi> of <hi>John</hi> 13. <hi>It is by the
Spirit we are drawn; being drawn, we come; being come we are enabled to walk
with God and Chriſt:</hi> It is this Spirit that doth all for us. As in the
<hi>Ecche,</hi> The Ayre being moved by the voice, returns the ſame ſound
by its own motion; So in all <pb facs="tcp:33666:11"/>our Communion with <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt;</hi> the Soul being moved by the <hi>Spirit,</hi> returns
anſwer, by vertue of the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> motion in us; Come, ſayes the
<hi>Spirit,</hi> I come ſayes the <hi>Soul,</hi> being taught by the ſame
<hi>Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the works wrought on the Souls of men, in order to Salvation,
are wrought of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in us, but by the
<hi>Spirit;</hi> As in theſe three ſpecial particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> By the <hi>Spirit</hi> they inſtruct and
teach; <hi>The Spirit is an enlightning Spirit, a Spirit of Judgement, and of
burning.</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> reveals the Counſels of <hi>God,</hi> the
great Miſteries of the Kingdom; Leads into all truth, makes men wiſe to
Salvation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> By this <hi>Spirit</hi> they quicken &amp;
comfort the Souls of men, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.5. It is by the <hi>Spirit</hi> that
<hi>the Love of God is ſhed abroad in our hearts.</hi> Our cold and frozen
<hi>Spirits</hi> are warmed and made fit for action, and by this
<hi>Spirit,</hi> we are awaken'd; Hence the <hi>Church</hi> prayes, for the
breathings of this <hi>Spirit, Cant.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Awake, O North-wind, and
come thou South, blow upon my Garden, that the Spices thereof may flow
out.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> By this <hi>Spirit</hi> they do ſtrengthen,
and eſtabliſh the hearts of men in the wayes of Holineſſe, thus they
are made ſtrong in the <hi>Lord,</hi> and in the power of his might; ſtrong
to reſiſt tentations, ſtrong to ſuppeſſe corruptions; ſtrong to
perform duties, by this <hi>Spirit</hi> they are carryed through all
difficulties; by this <hi>Spirit</hi> their Infirmities are healed;<note place="margin">Rom. 8.26.</note> they are made to perſevere, and kept
<hi>ſtedfaſt, and unmoveable, alwayes abounding in the work of the
Lord;</hi> and <hi>Sealed up to the day of Redemption.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> do make their abode with
them that keep the words of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> till they come to make an
ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting abode with them in Heaven.</p>
            <p>And according to the workings of this <hi>Spirit</hi> more or
leſſe in the hearts of men, <hi>God</hi> is ſaid to be
<hi>preſent,</hi> or <hi>abſent</hi> from his people.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſons. </seg>
               </label> Secondly, <hi>The Reaſons
why God and Chriſt will make their abode with them that keep his
words.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Becauſe
of their ſpecial Love to, and Care of them that keep his words. Indeed all
the Care of <hi>God,</hi> in concerning his people, that he hath in the World,
there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in the Second Commandement, he is ſaid <hi>to ſhew mercy 
<pb facs="tcp:33666:11"/>to thouſands of them that fear him, and keep his
Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> that do not <hi>caſt his word behind their backs,</hi>
and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaking his Appointments, <hi>follow their own Inventions;</hi> So
that if we faithfully keep his word, he will abide with us in our work; And
this is the Great Reaſon in the Text, <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther will Love him;</hi> Not
but that he Loves his Elect from Eternity, but he will manifeſt his Love to
them, and therefore <hi>he will make his abode with them,</hi> as the People of
his Love; for in <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.9. <hi>The Lords Portion is his People, and
Jacob is the Lot of his Inheritance,</hi> and in <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. they are
called <hi>his Jewels,</hi> and <hi>men will abide with their
Treaſure.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Becauſe of
the near Relation that is between <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> and them
that keep his word. That is a very full place of Scripture for this purpoſe,
<hi>Mat.</hi> 12.50. <hi>Whoſoever ſhall do the will of my Father which is
in Heaven, the ſame is my Brother, and Siſter, and Mother.</hi> What nearer
Relation can there be than this? So near are they to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
that keep his word, obſerve his will, and be true and faithful to his
Appointments; and ſure ſuch near Relations will deſire Cohabitation on
both ſides.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> are ſaid to ſtand
Related in a <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Relation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> They are ſaid to ſtand Related in a
<hi>Conjugal Relation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtand in a
<hi>Paternal Relation</hi> to his People.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, God</hi> is their <hi>Father,</hi> and they are his
<hi>Sons</hi> and <hi>Daughters;</hi> And this the <hi>Church</hi> doth
acknowledge in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.16. <hi>Doubtleſs thou art our Father,
though</hi> Abraham <hi>be ignorant of us, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>acknowledge us
not, thou O Lord art our Father,</hi> &amp;c. And with this the Lord comforted
mourning Zion, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 49.14,15. <hi>But</hi> Zion <hi>ſaid, The
Lord hath forſaken me, and my Lord hath forgotten me.</hi> But <hi>God</hi>
ſayes, <hi>Can a Woman forget her ſucking Child, that ſhe ſhould not
have Compaſſion on the Son of her womb? Yea, they may forget, yet I will
not forget thee. Behold I have graven thee on the palms of my Hands,</hi>
&amp;c. My abode is with thee.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Jeſus Christ</hi> is their <hi>Father,
Iſai.</hi> 9.6. <hi>The everlaſting Father.</hi> Therefore he promiſeth
his Diſciples in <pb facs="tcp:33666:12"/>this, 14. <hi>Joh.</hi> 18. <hi>I will not
leave you,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>,
<hi>Orphans,</hi> or <hi>Fatherleſſe Children.</hi> He is the moſt
affectionate tender hearted Father, <hi>Tam Pater nemo, tam pius nemo: None
ſo good, none ſuch a Father as he,</hi> (<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Tertul.</hi>)</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſtand related to
them that keep his word, in a <hi>Conjugal relation;</hi> and <hi>God</hi> hath
ſaid a ſpecial command of co-habitation upon perſons in this relation,
<hi>The man muſt dwell with his own Wife.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, God</hi> is related as a <hi>Husband,</hi> And will
not <hi>God</hi> dwell with his People, whom he hath eſpouſed to himſelf?
<hi>I have betrothed thee unto me for ever,</hi> (Hoſea 2.19.) <hi>Yea I will
betroth thee unto me in righteouſneſs, and in judgement, and in loving
kindneſs, and in mercies; I will even betroth thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me in
faithfulneſs.</hi> And in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 54.5,6. <hi>For thy Maker is thy
Husband,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>For the Lord hath called thee as a Woman
forſaken,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> is the <hi>Husband</hi> of his
People, as we ſee in the whole Book of <hi>Canticles.</hi> And ſo in
<hi>Ephe.</hi> 5. from the 29. Verſe to the end of the Chapter. Now where
ſhall <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> make their abode, but with their
eſpouſed Ones? Doth <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> delight to lodge any where
more than with the <hi>Wife</hi> of his boſome?</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Reaſ. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Becauſe of
<hi>Gods</hi> faithful Covenant, he will make his abode with them that keep his
word. If we keep the word of his Patience, he will keep the word of his
Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Revel.</hi> 3.10. <hi>Becauſe thou haſt kept the word of my
Pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, I alſo will keep thee, from the hour of temptation, which ſhall
come on all the world, to try them that dwell upon the earth.</hi> It is called
a word of Patience, becauſe it teacheth patience, and eſpecially becauſe
it requires it in all them that will obſerve it. And this is <hi>Gods</hi>'s
<hi>Covenant.</hi> Now, what is the Covenant? <hi>Jerem.</hi> 32.40. <hi>And I
will make an everlaſting Covenant with them, that I will not turn away from
them, to do them good; but I will put my fear in their hearts, that they
ſhall not depart from me;</hi> and ſuch a ſure and infallible promiſe
of abode, can never be violated by a <hi>God-keeping</hi> Covenant; <hi>God may
hide for a moment, turn away in a little wrath from his people</hi> (Iſa.
54.8.9.10.11.) <hi>but with great mercy will he gather them, and ſhew them
everlaſting kindneſs;</hi> Yea, his Promiſe ſhall be as the waters of
<hi>Noah,</hi> that as the waters of the great <hi>Deluge</hi> ſhall never
co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <pb facs="tcp:33666:12"/>the world any more, ſo he will never forſake his people
utterly. It ſhall be more poſſible for the Mountains to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part, and the
Hills to be removed, than that he ſhould fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally depart from <hi>His.</hi>
The frame of the world may be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordered, but the frame of <hi>Gods</hi>
heart towards his People, can never be changed. When the men of the world think
<hi>God</hi> hath forſaken them, he is near to them, and cannot caſt off
his people; He may ſometimes give them up for their ſinnes into the enemies
hands, but cannot give them away: this gave the <hi>Church</hi> that
confidence, in <hi>Micah</hi> 7.8. <hi>Rejoyce not againſt me, O mine Enemy;
when I fall, I ſhall ariſe, when I ſit in darkneſs, the Lord ſhall be
a light unto me.</hi> And this did bear the head of the
<hi>New-Teſtament-Saints</hi> above wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.8.9. <hi>We are
troubled on every ſide, yet not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed; we are perplexed, but not
in diſpair; perſecuted, but not forſaken; caſt down, but not
deſtroyed.</hi> And whence is it, that <hi>Diſtreſs</hi> doth not follow
<hi>Troubles? Despair</hi> our <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexities? Deſertion</hi> our
<hi>Perſecutions? Deſtruction</hi> our <hi>ſad Dejections?</hi> ſure it
is, becauſe <hi>God is faithful,</hi> alwayes with us, <hi>and will not
ſuffer us to be tempted above what we are able to bear,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 10.13.</note>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partic. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> What a
ſpecial bleſſing it is, to a perſon, or peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, to have <hi>God</hi>
and <hi>Chriſt</hi> to make their abode with them.</p>
            <p>The excellency and deſirableneſs of this abode of <hi>God</hi>
and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with Believers, may be ſeen in theſe three
parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It is better than all outward mercies, and
earthly bleſſings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This will more than ſupply the want or
abſence of all other comforts.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> All our happineſs doth lye in this, <hi>Gods
preſence with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Conſ. </seg>1</label> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The abode of
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with a ſoul, is better than all outward
mercies, or earthly bleſſings whatſoever. <hi>God</hi> was wont to tell
his people heretofore, as in <hi>Deut.</hi> 28. <hi>That if they would keep his
Commandments, they ſhould be bleſſed in their basket, and in their
ſtore; that he would give them peace, the fat heritage of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and
to ride upon the high places;</hi> all goodly mercies: But now he doth
encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage <pb facs="tcp:33666:13"/>them by a bleſſing of far greater worth, <hi>I will
love you, I will make mine abode with you.</hi> It is ſo high and
tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent a favour, That <hi>Moſes</hi> preferr'd it, before that
goodly Land of promiſe, <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Land flowing with Milk and Hony,
as appears by that paſſage in <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.15. <hi>If thy preſence
go not with me, carry us not up hence.</hi> Though <hi>Canaan</hi> be never
ſo deſirable a good Land, Yet rather let me abide in this vaſt-howling
Wilderneſſe with God, then go without thy preſence thither. A
Wilderneſſe Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Tent,</hi> is better
then all Pleaſures and Honours without God in the <hi>Palace.</hi> Hence
<hi>David</hi> in the midſt of all his Royal Pompe, and Greatneſſe,
deſired this, as the Complement and Perfection of all, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
101.1.2. <hi>O when wilt thou come unto me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Conſider theſe two particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That there is not beauty, nor
deſirableneſſe in the faireſt outward proſperity, if <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt</hi> do not make their abode with us. If we have all the world,
and cannot ſee the abode of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> on our
Tabernacle, in their ſpecial Providence, in Soul refreſhing Ordinances, or
by the Comforting Spirit; We may look on all, and ſay as <hi>Hiram</hi> did
of the Cities <hi>Solomon</hi> gave him, they be <hi>Cabul, Dirty
things.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 9.13.</note> If we cannot find
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> thus with us, in the midſt of our Glory,
<hi>The Glory is departed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, There is no miſery, nor
unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in the worſt afflictions, if <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt</hi> be there; in the <hi>Furnace</hi> there is no <hi>Death;</hi>
in <hi>Captivity,</hi> no <hi>Darkneſſe;</hi> in <hi>Priſon,</hi> no
<hi>Sadneſſe;</hi> in <hi>Death,</hi> no <hi>Hell. Jeſus Chriſt</hi>
tells us, <hi>he will not leave us Comfortleſſe;</hi> he never told us we
ſhould not meet with Tribulations, but ſayes, <hi>In the world we ſhall
have Tribulation,</hi> and as ſurely, <hi>that in him, we ſhall have
Conſolation.</hi> His people may be in the world Friendleſſe,
Harbourleſſe, Pennyleſſe, but he aſſures them, they ſhall never
be Comfortleſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Partic. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This abode
of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with his people, will more then ſupply
the want or abſence of all other things. <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> when he
would throughly encourage his Diſciples againſt all the hardſhips, and
diſcouraging fears, they might meet withall after his departure, gives them
this one precious <hi>Cordial,</hi> or <hi>Catholicon,</hi> in <hi>Mat.</hi>
28.20. <pb facs="tcp:33666:13"/>
               <hi>Loe I am with you alway, even unto the end of the
World, when you are caſt out of the Synagogues, had before Magiſtrates and
Rulers for my name ſake, Scourged, Hated, Impriſoned; for all theſe
things ſhall they do unto you, Let this comfort you; Loe, I am with you
alway, to the end of the World.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Indeed, This abode of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with his
people, is every thing to the Soul, which we may ſee in theſe three
particulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Their preſence is <hi>a Sanctuary, and ſure
Hide-ing place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is <hi>a ſure Light and Guide to
them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> It is a <hi>Store-houſe and Treaſury of all
Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The abode or
preſence of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of a
<hi>Sanctuary, or ſure hideing place;</hi> as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 84.11. <hi>For
the Lord God is a Sun and Shield, &amp;c.</hi> and in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 8.13.
ſayes the Prophet, <hi>Sanctifie the Lord God of Hoſts, and let him be your
fear, and let him be your dread, and he ſhall be for a Sanctuary:</hi> Do you
ſet <hi>God</hi> before you, and he will ſet himſelf by you; and where
the great <hi>God goes,</hi> there <hi>goes a Guard of Angels,</hi> Pſal.
34.7. <hi>His Wings be a Covert, and his hand a Canopy, with which he hides
from the Storm, and from Rain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that he is a mighty Saviour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider his <hi>Omnipotency;</hi> He can do
whatever pleaſeth him; He can make <hi>the worm Jacob to threſh Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains,
and the Mountains to become a plague before Jerubba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel;</hi> Zach. 4.7.
<hi>All the Nations of the Earth are but as a drop of the Bucket, or duſt of
the Ballance, compared with him; and all hearts are in his hands;</hi>
Therefore ſayes the Prophet, in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 26.4. <hi>Truſt in the
Lord for ever, for in the Lord</hi> Jeho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vah, <hi>is everlaſting ſtrength,
or the</hi> Rock <hi>of ages.</hi> He is no broken Reed, but that ſtrength in
which we may Confide; As <hi>David</hi> ſayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46.1,2,3. Si
fractus illabitur Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis, <hi>If the World be diſſolved, God is our refuge
and ſtrength,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>therefore we will not fear, though the Earth
be removed, and though the Mountains be carried into the midſt of the
Sea,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly,</hi>
Conſider his imme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>tability; We
have ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Comfort in the unchangeableneſſe of this <hi>God,</hi>
Mal. 3.6. <pb facs="tcp:33666:14"/>
               <hi>I am the Lord, I change not; therefore ye Sons of
Jacob are not conſumed.</hi> And for this we have the experience of
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, Pſal.</hi> 9.10. <hi>They that know thy name, will put their
truſt in thee, for thou (Lord) haſt not forſaken them that ſeek
thee,</hi> and the Churches experience, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 63.9. <hi>he bear
them, and he carried them all the daies of old.</hi> This great and
unchangeable <hi>Saviour,</hi> ſaves his people, theſe four wayes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> He will ſave and preſerve from Evils, and
will be a Chamber of ſafety when the Indignation is abroad, to hide from the
ſtorm; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 11.6. <hi>Yet will I be to them as a little Sanctuary
in the Countries where they ſhall come, I will be with thee;</hi> is
<hi>Gods</hi> great <hi>Promiſe,</hi> and his <hi>Peoples Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity;</hi> it
was <hi>Joſhua's</hi> Guard, and <hi>Jeremiah's</hi> Braſen-Wall.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> He will ſave his people in afflictions; as he
did the three Children in the burning Fornace, thus he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livers <hi>in ſix
troubles, and alſo in ſeven;</hi> as 'tis promiſed in <hi>Iſai.</hi>
43.2,3. <hi>When thou paſſeſt thorough the waters I will be with thee and
thorow the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee; When thou walkeſt thorow
the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame kindle upon
thee, For I am the Lord thy God, the Holy one of Iſrael, thy Saviour.
Job's</hi> experience is an everlaſting proof of this, that when the Lead is
Conſumed, the Gold is preſerved in the Fornace.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> He will ſave or deliver out of afflictions, 1
<hi>Cor.</hi> 10, 13. <hi>In the midſt of all temptations, he will make a way
for us to eſcape them, Many are the troubles of the Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but the Lord
delivereth them out of all.</hi> He is <hi>Emmanu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, God</hi> with us; Our
Redeemer from Hell, and from Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> He will ſave by afflictions, and by the evils
they meet withall; <hi>Prov.</hi> 29.15. <hi>The Rod and Reproof give
wiſdom;</hi> and as <hi>David</hi> ſayes, <hi>It was good for me that I was
afflicted.</hi> All things ſhall work for good, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.7.
<hi>Theſe afflictions work for us a far more exceeding and eternal weight of
Glory.</hi> The Veſſel is uſually covered with Dirt by the Clenſers
hand, that it may ſhine with the more brightneſs; So by afflictions
<hi>God</hi> makes us partakers of his Holineſs.</p>
            <p>Afflictions and outward evils, come alike to all, but with much
different effect; All men fall into afflictions, Good and Bad, but as the
<hi>Iſraelites,</hi> and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> went both <pb facs="tcp:33666:14"/>into
the <hi>Red Sea,</hi> and the one was drowned, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther paſſed
throrough to <hi>Canaan:</hi> So the Righteous and the Wicked fall under
Calamity, the one ſinks through unbelief, and the other paſſes thorough
ſafety, <hi>and by Faith and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience comes to inherit the
promiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The Abode or
Preſence of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with Believers, is inſtead
of a ſure Guide and Light unto them; They can never want a Guide, who have
<hi>God</hi> with them. As the Pillar of a Cloud by day, and of Fire by night,
was unto <hi>Iſrael</hi> in all their March, The ſame and more is
<hi>God</hi> to his People, in all their Pilgrimage.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſider three things.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider, that Man cannot be without this
Guide; The beſt of men have very great need of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of
<hi>God</hi> to lead them; that they be not miſ-led, and that they don't
faint in the way, <hi>What can the Sheep do with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Shepheard?</hi> Such is
<hi>God</hi> to his, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23.1. without <hi>Gods</hi> abode with
us, 'tis as Children without a Father, and none to direct them, and ſo left
to run themſelves into miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chief; What is the World without a Sun?
<hi>Jer.</hi> 10.23. <hi>The way of man is not in himſelf, it is not in man
that walketh to direct his ſteps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, that 'tis our great wiſdom to
commit our way to the guidance of this <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
Every wiſe man will commit his way to <hi>God,</hi> and not move a ſtep
without him; as <hi>Moſes</hi> in the Conduct of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> would not
move a foot without <hi>God.</hi> That was a good Petition, or rather
Reſolution of <hi>David,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.24. <hi>Thou ſhalt
guide me with thy Counſel, and afterward receive me to Glory.</hi> I am
reſolved to be guided by <hi>Gods Counſel,</hi> and an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent and
imitable practiſe of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> in <hi>Gen.</hi> 26.24,25. that where
he had met <hi>God</hi> at <hi>Beer-ſheba,</hi> and where <hi>God</hi> had
bleſſed him, There he pitched his Tent; So we ſhould move as <hi>God</hi>
leads.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider, That if <hi>God</hi> undertake to
Guide us, we ſhall not miſcarry, he will certainly bring us ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e to Heaven. Our feet may be almoſt
gone, but ſhall not be altogether gone, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.2. <hi>My feet
were almoſt gone, my ſteps had well nigh ſlipt.</hi> So it may be with
the choiceſt of <hi>Gods</hi> Servants; but in the 23 <hi>verſe,
Nevertheleſſe I am <pb facs="tcp:33666:15"/>continually with thee; thou haſt holden
me by my right hand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The more dark and dangerous the times be, the more we ſhould
deſire <hi>Gods</hi> abode with us; the nearer a night of trouble or of death
is to us, the more earneſtly beg his ſtay, as the two <hi>Diſciples,
Luke</hi> 24.29. <hi>They conſtrained Chriſt, ſaying, abide with us, for
it is towards Evening, and the day is far ſpent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The abode or
preſence of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with his people, is inſtead
of a Treaſury and Store-houſe of all Proviſions. Where <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt</hi> is, and where <hi>God</hi> makes his abode, there is a Spring
head of comforts, that cannot be drawn dry, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 33.16. <hi>Bread
ſhall be given them, and their waters ſhall be ſure, who have God with
them;</hi> So was <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Iſrael, Deut.</hi> 29.5.6. <hi>He fed
Iſrael in the wilderneſs forty years, their clothes did not wax old. You
have not eaten bread, neither have you drunk wine, or ſtrong drink, that ye
might know that I am the Lord your God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſider three particulars here.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider <hi>God is ſuch a ſtore,</hi>
that he is alwayes full; He hath an <hi>Antarchy</hi> in himſelf, and ſaies
to his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 81.10. <hi>Open thy mouth wide, and I
will fill it, ask what you will, and there 'tis to be had.</hi> There be full
Treaſures, of temporal and ſpiritual good things with them, with whom
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> do make their abode. As the <hi>Ark</hi> of
<hi>God</hi> brought all kind of bleſſings to the houſe of
<hi>Obed-edom,</hi> ſo when <hi>God</hi> comes, he brings all things;
<hi>Deus meus, &amp; omnia;</hi> My <hi>God,</hi> and all things. When
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> came to <hi>Zacheus,</hi> he tells him, <hi>This day
is Salvation come to thine houſe;</hi> that is, both temporal and ſpiritual
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervations and deliverances; Salvation doth conſiſt in the total
abſence of all evil, and in the preſence and poſſeſſion of all
good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> have left with us the
promiſes of the Covenant to live upon, till we come to the inheritance of the
purchaſed Poſſeſſion: Theſe be like the <hi>Widows Cruſe,</hi>
that never fails; this like the <hi>Manna,</hi> will not be with-held while we
be in the wilderneſs, till we come into <hi>Canaan,</hi> to feed on the
fruits of that Land, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.5. That's a ſure Promiſe, in which we
may by faith ſee preſent ſupplies, <hi>I <pb facs="tcp:33666:15"/>will never leave
thee, nor forſake thee;</hi> and in <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.19. we may
poſſeſſe in that Promiſe whatever we want; <hi>My God ſhall
ſupply all your need, according to his riches in glory, by Chriſt
Jeſus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, God</hi> hath given us his <hi>Son,</hi> and
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> hath given us <hi>himſelf,</hi> as an enſuing
pledge of all mercies con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the promiſes, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.32. <hi>He
that ſpared not his own Son, but gave him for us, how ſhall he not with him
alſo freely give us all things;</hi> He that hath not ſpared his Son, will
not with-hold any mercies; he that hath given us the beſt of bleſſings,
will not with-hold ſmaller mercies: He doth al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way tell his people, as in 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 12.9. <hi>My grace is ſufficient for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> The abode of
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with Believers, is their Heaven upon Earth.
All our happineſs is in the abode of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with
us.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider it is a wonderful mercy of the great
<hi>God,</hi> that by his common Providence, he is with the works of his hands,
which is mans ſafety; and <hi>David</hi> admires at this, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
8.4. <hi>Lord what is man, that thou art mindful of him? and the Son of man,
that thou viſiteſt him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider it is a mercy of the greateſt
worth, and to be for ever admired, that <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> do
not only viſit us by common Providence and Inſpection, as his crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures,
but make their abode with us, as with children and friends; O this is our
glory; <hi>God</hi> doth not come with a ſhort viſit, for a day, for a few
days, <hi>but makes an ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting abode.</hi> The Church complained when
ſhe thought <hi>God</hi> was departed, becauſe he had been with them, and
made ſo ſhort a ſtay, <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.8. <hi>Why ſhouldſt thou be as
a ſtranger in the Land, and as a way-faring man, that turneth aſide to
tarry for a night,</hi> &amp;c. but when ſhe remembred the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of
eternal abode, ſhe comforts her ſelf, in the 9. <hi>verſe. Yet thou O
Lord art in the midſt of us.</hi> To be ever with the <hi>Lord,</hi> is all
we can hope for, and it is mans contemplative happineſſe, to converſe in
his thoughts with that Glory.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> hath
promiſed this, as our great Glory, and full reward; <hi>I will take you to my
ſelf, they ſhall behold my glory.</hi>
               <note place="margin">17. Joh. verſe
24.</note> 1 Epiſt. Joh. 3.2. <hi>We ſhall be like him,
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> we ſhall ſee him as he
is.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:16"/>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> This abode with <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> is the higheſt <hi>option,</hi> and aim of all the people
of <hi>God.</hi> This was <hi>Pauls</hi> preſſings, in <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.
<hi>That he might attain to the reſurrection of the dead, (i.)</hi> the
ſtate of them that are riſen, and with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
Therefore reſolves after a long debate with himſelf, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.21.
<hi>To be with Chriſt, is beſt of all,</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 73. at the latter end, profeſſes, <hi>He had none in
Heaven but God, and there was none upon earth that he deſired in compariſon
of him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe </seg>1</label> Uſe. <hi>Firſt,</hi> of
<hi>Lamentation, and laments three ſorts of perſons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let us lament <hi>ſuch as be without</hi> God
<hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>in the world,</hi> all <hi>ignorant</hi> and
<hi>ungodly</hi> perſons; yea, this is the ſad caſe of all the
<hi>Sons</hi> of <hi>Adam,</hi> ever ſince he ſinned, and loſt communion
with his <hi>God;</hi> They be brought forth into the world, with their
<hi>backs</hi> upon <hi>God,</hi> and with <hi>Gods face</hi> againſt them:
What was <hi>Cain</hi>'s grief? how was his heart hurried into a world of
inconceivable diſtempers, and diſtracting thoughts? when he muſt be
turn'd out of <hi>Gods</hi> preſence, from the enjoyment of <hi>God</hi> in
his <hi>Ordinances, Gen.</hi> 4.14. <hi>Behold, thou haſt driven me out this
day,</hi> (ſaies poor <hi>Cain,</hi>) <hi>from the face of the earth,</hi>
(but this is as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing) <hi>and from thy face ſhall I be hid,</hi> (and now
where is my comfort and ſafety?) <hi>it ſhall come to paſſe, that every
one that findeth me, ſhall ſlay me.</hi> Such perſons be as Lambs in a
large place, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 4.16. <hi>Without a Keeper in their moſt
plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiful state;</hi> What hope have ſuch to eſcape <hi>Hell</hi> and
<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſider theſe two particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider it is a very ſad caſe, when
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> withdraw, or depart but for a moment; 'tis a
ſad, and into<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerable <hi>moment,</hi> as we ſee in the complaint of
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> when <hi>God</hi> withdrew himſelf from him; <hi>My God,
my God, why haſt thou forſaken me?</hi> and in the example of <hi>David,
Aſaph</hi> and <hi>Heman,</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. and <hi>Pſal.</hi>
88. and the whole <hi>Church</hi> laments in <hi>Jer.</hi> 14.8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider if <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt</hi> do never come to make their abode with us here, we are never
like to make our abode <hi>with them hereafter;</hi> and then it were better we
had never been born, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 73.27. <hi>They that are far from 
<pb facs="tcp:33666:16"/>thee, ſhall periſh.</hi> And this is Hell, to be ſeparated
from <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.8.9. They,
<hi>(i.)</hi> the <hi>wicked</hi> ſhall be puniſhed with everlaſting
deſtruction, from the preſence of the <hi>Lord,</hi> and from the glory of
his power. It is <hi>Heaven</hi> where-ever <hi>God</hi> is in his ſpecial
abode, and that is <hi>Hell</hi> where He is not preſent in his mercy and
grace.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly, Uſe of
Lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us <hi>lament</hi> over a <hi>worſe ſort of men,</hi> and
they be ſuch as in <hi>Job.</hi> 21.14. <hi>That ſay to God, depart from
us, for we deſire not the knowledge of thy wayes;</hi> That refuſe the word
of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and be weary of <hi>God</hi> and his <hi>Ordinances,</hi>
and ſo reject <hi>God.</hi> as if one houſe could not hold them both; as
the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 30.10.11. <hi>Who ſay to the Seers, ſee not; and
to the Prophets, prophecy not,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Cauſe the Holy one to ceaſe
from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us.</hi> They that ſtop the mouths of them that ſpeak the word
of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> or turn away their ears from harkening to that which is
ſpoken, ſay in effect, <hi>Let God be gone, let Chriſt depart from
us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider what an evil frame of
<hi>ſpirit</hi> it is, for men to refuſe the preſence of <hi>God.</hi>
Was there ever wickedneſs like this? that the great <hi>God</hi> ſhould be
as an <hi>unbidden gueſt</hi> with his own creatures, and have no better
entertainment than <hi>Chriſt</hi> with the <hi>Gaderens,</hi> who beſought
him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part out of their Coaſt, yea, which is far worſe,
<hi>rejected,</hi> as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was by the poſſeſſed in the
<hi>Goſpel, Mat.</hi> 8.29. <hi>What have we to do with thee? art thou come
to torment us before the time?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider it will be a very terrible day, when
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> depart from ſuch perſons. <hi>God</hi>
threatens it as a ſore judgement upon <hi>Jeruſalem, Jer.</hi> 6.8. <hi>Be
thou in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed O</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>leſt my Soul depart from
thee;</hi> When <hi>God</hi> departs, in comes all Judgements, for it follows
in the Text, <hi>Leſt I make thee deſolate;</hi> Deſolation comes as
ſoon as <hi>God</hi> is gone, yea, ſaies the <hi>Lord, Hoſ.</hi> 9.12.
<hi>Woe to them, when I depart from them.</hi> And though he depart from ſuch
by removing his <hi>Counſells, Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Ordinances:</hi> He
will ſtill be with them in <hi>judgement;</hi> when he is far from their
<hi>Affections,</hi> he will be nigh to their <hi>Conſciences,</hi> then he
will ſhew his terrour, and his wrath; and then they ſhall find, that as
there is not a <hi>ſweeter promiſe</hi> than this, <hi>I will never 
<pb facs="tcp:33666:17"/>leave thee nor forſake thee;</hi> ſo not a more <hi>terrible
judgement</hi> than this, <hi>I will not love thee, nor abide with
thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, <hi>Uſe of
Lamentation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us lament our ſelves, who have had <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt</hi> making their abode with us for many years in their ſpecial
<hi>Providence, Gospel Ordinances,</hi> &amp;c. Yet we have not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved ſo
glorious a <hi>Preſence,</hi> ſo rich a mercy: eſpecially we have cauſe
to lament this four-fold neglect.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That we have ſo little acquainted our ſelves
with <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſo little prized and obſerved
their <hi>Preſence</hi> with us, that we have learn'd no more of <hi>God</hi>
and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> but are yet ſtrangers to them; ſo that <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt</hi> may ſay to us, as in <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.9. <hi>Have I been ſo
long time with you, and yet haſt thou not known me, Philip;</hi> ſo he may
ſay to us, Have I been ſo long time with you in my <hi>Providences,
Ordinances, and by my Spirit,</hi> and yet have you not known my
<hi>Goodneſs,</hi> my <hi>Faithfulneſs,</hi> my <hi>Name,</hi> my
<hi>Laws</hi> and <hi>Ordinances?</hi> Sure it is with moſt of us, as with
<hi>Jacob, Gen.</hi> 28.15.16. The <hi>Lord</hi> was with him, and he was in
his Dream, and when he awaked, he ſaid, <hi>Surely the Lord is in this place,
and I knew it not.</hi> So <hi>God</hi> hath been with us, but we have been in
a dream, or in a ſleep all this while; but when <hi>God</hi> ſhall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waken
us, we ſhall ſay with him, <hi>God was in this place, and we knew it
not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We may lament our ſelves that we have ſo
little conformed to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt. God</hi> hath been with us,
but we have refuſed his company, as <hi>Ephe.</hi> 2.12. <hi>And had our
converſation as without God, and without Chriſt in the world;</hi> O when
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhall depart from us, it will be a
heart-breaking to us, and we ſhall dearly repent the leaſt
miſcarriages.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We may lament, that we have not lived more upon
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> to truſt in them, and depend upon them
for life and Salvation, and made him our <hi>Counſellour, Guide,</hi> and
<hi>Strength,</hi> and lived upon his All-ſufficiency; we have not made them
our <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> our <hi>Treaſury,</hi> our <hi>Hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs,</hi>
though they have been with us, <hi>in whom are all things.</hi> Yet have we
lived at ſo poor a rate (as to our ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual comforts) as if we had been
under the <hi>Hypocrit's</hi> Curſe, <hi>Job</hi> 20.22. <hi>In the fulneſs
of his ſufficiency he is in <pb facs="tcp:33666:17"/>ſtraits,</hi> Or guilty of that
vanity mentioned in <hi>Eccle.</hi> 6.2. <hi>To have Riches and Honours.</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>and not a heart to uſe them.</hi> To have a <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> in whom are all <hi>Riches</hi> and <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours,</hi> and
have had no <hi>Faith</hi> to uſe them for our <hi>comfort,</hi> we have even
ſtarved our ſelves at the fulleſt Table, and Spring-head of plenty.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We may lament our ſelves, that we have not
taken more pleaſure in the enjoyment of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> in
the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Goſpel Ordinances;</hi> accounting all
Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and delights, ſolitarineſſe, in compariſon of the joy and
comfort that is in the abode of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
eſpecially, when <hi>God</hi> expects we ſhould rejoyce in him, and hath
pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to abode with ſuch, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 64.5. <hi>Thou meeteſt him
that rejoyceth, and worketh Righteouſneſſe, and remembreth thee in thy
wayes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Uſe. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Two Uſes of
Exhortation.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>To get the Preſence of</hi> God <hi>and</hi>
Chriſt <hi>with us.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 2. <hi>To endeavour to keep</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt
<hi>abiding with us.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>The firſt</hi> Uſe of
Exhortation.</p>
            <p>Let us be Exhorted above all deſires, to deſire <hi>Gods</hi>
pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence; and above all getting, Get <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> to
make their abode with you. O with what Ardency and heat of deſire, doth
<hi>David</hi> expreſſe himſelf; <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4. <hi>One thing
have I deſired of the Lord, that will I ſeek after, that I may dwell in the
houſe of the Lord all the dayes of my life, to behold the beauty of the Lord,
and to enquire in his Temple;</hi> and ſo in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 42.1,2. <hi>As
the Hart pants after the water brooks, ſo panteth my Soul after thee O God,
My Soul thirſteth for God, when ſhall I come and appear before God? O when
wilt thou come unto me?</hi> and in a multitude of ſuch like
<hi>Pathetick</hi> breathings after <hi>God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that we may the more earneſtly deſire this mercy, the
<hi>abode</hi> of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with <hi>us;</hi>
Conſider three par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider, the preſence of <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> is the ſpecial favour and honour that <hi>God</hi>
beſtows only upon his own people. By this was <hi>Iſrael</hi>
diſtinguiſhed from all the world, <hi>Exod.</hi> 33.16. <hi>My preſence
ſhall go with thee,</hi> and in the laſt <hi>verſe</hi> of the laſt
<hi>Chapter</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel. It is the Church only that is call'd</hi>
Jehovah Shammah. The <hi>Lord</hi> is there her <pb facs="tcp:33666:18"/>
               <hi>Founder,
Preſerver,</hi> and <hi>Governour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, that they that have <hi>God</hi>
and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with them, dwell continually at the Fountain Head of
Conſolations, as <hi>David</hi> ſayes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 23. <hi>I ſhall
want nothing, The Lord is my ſhepheard, My Cup runs over. Surely
Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and Mercy ſhall follow me all the daies of my life.</hi> This
<hi>Fountain</hi> keeps our <hi>Ciſternes</hi> full; our Channels <hi>run
ſhallow</hi> ſometimes, but never are they <hi>dryed up; Hoſ.</hi> 14.5.
<hi>I will be as the Dew unto Iſrael; He ſhall grow as the Lillie, and
caſt forth his roots as Lebanon,</hi> they ſhall grow up as the Lillie,
<hi>beautiful</hi> and <hi>fair,</hi> and as the Cedar, <hi>well rooted</hi>
and <hi>eſtabliſhed;</hi> He that hath the <hi>Sun,</hi> hath
<hi>Light,</hi> He that hath the <hi>Well,</hi> muſt needs have <hi>Water;
Ille poſſidet omnia, qui poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det poſſidentem omnia;</hi> He hath
all things, who hath him from whom all things come.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Conſider, that when all Comforts leave us,
<hi>God</hi> will not; when Friends forſake, and Riches profit not, in the
evil <hi>day, God is a preſent help in time of trouble,</hi> and loves to
ſhew himſelf in <hi>Dubiis &amp; Arduis,</hi> in the greateſt
difficulties, and on the <hi>Mount of ſtraits. Jeſus Chriſt</hi> ſayes
<hi>truly</hi> to us, what <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid <hi>raſhly</hi> to him;
<hi>Though all forſake thee, yet will not I.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Object.</hi> I have found
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> gone from me, ſayes the <hi>Soul,</hi>
when I have had need of him.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Anſwer,</hi> Firſt, That
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> may and do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times hide their faces
from their deareſt Friends.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Though <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> do
ſometimes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw from us, yet every <hi>interruption</hi> of Communion, is
not a <hi>ſeparation;</hi> The <hi>Sun</hi> doth not ceaſe <hi>to be,</hi>
when it cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth <hi>to ſhine.</hi> Grace may ſuſpend <hi>its
acting,</hi> but doth not looſe <hi>its being, God</hi> will not finally
forſake his <hi>People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, God</hi> hath very many Gracious ends, why he
ſometimes withdraws; And they are alway in mercy to his people, <hi>ſad
providences, producing ſweet effects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>Directions and helps, how to
get the preſence of God and Chriſt with us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Repent and humble
your ſelves, becauſe of all your ſins, that you have at any time rejected
the Counſels of <hi>God,</hi> and refuſed <hi>Grace</hi> and
<hi>Mercy,</hi> and neglected <hi>Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunities,</hi> of doing you
<hi>Souls</hi> good, and drawing near to <pb facs="tcp:33666:18"/>
               <hi>God; Repentance and
Reſolution against Sin, come like John Baptiſt,</hi> to prepare a way, and
a place, for <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> to come <hi>to,</hi> and make
their abode <hi>in.</hi> Of the <hi>Hearts</hi> and <hi>Houſes</hi> of
Impenitent Sinners, we may well ſay <hi>God is not there.</hi> The way to
have <hi>God</hi> to <hi>turn in unto us;</hi> is to <hi>turn away from
ſin,</hi> as <hi>Ephraim, Jer.</hi> 31.18,19,20. <hi>He</hi> bemoaned
himſelf, and repented, and <hi>God</hi> came to him as to his dear Son, and
to his pleaſant Child.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Believe in
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and by faith get an inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in him; It is by
faith only that we give entertainment to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> It is by
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> alone, that <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> come
together. <hi>No man hath ſeen the Father at any time, but the Son, and he to
whom he doth reveal him, and he that hath the Son, hath the Father,</hi> Rom.
5.1. <hi>Being juſtified by faith, we have peace with God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Own <hi>Jeſus
Chriſt</hi> in all his <hi>Offices,</hi> as your <hi>King, Prieſt,</hi> and
<hi>Prophet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, As your King,</hi> Let him have the Soveraignty of
your Souls, that he may rule over you. If <hi>Chriſt</hi> be your <hi>King,
God</hi> will be your <hi>Father; God</hi> loves to come, where
<hi>Chriſt</hi> hath his <hi>Throne.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, As your Prieſt,</hi> That his
<hi>Righteouſneſſe</hi> may give you the advantage of <hi>Communion</hi>
with <hi>God;</hi> without which we cannot <hi>come near to him,</hi> and he
will not <hi>come near to us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, As your Prophet,</hi> That he may ſhew you the way;
If his <hi>Spirit</hi> be your <hi>Guide,</hi> and his <hi>Word</hi> your
<hi>Rule,</hi> you may be ſure his <hi>Promiſes</hi> ſhall be your
<hi>Portion,</hi> even this <hi>Promiſe</hi> in the Text, <hi>They will come
to you, and make their abode with you,</hi> even <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Seek
earneſtly after <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> in the uſe of all
appointed means, till you come to ſee, and enjoy their preſence with
you.</p>
            <p>Here ſhall be ſhewn theſe two particulars.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Where we may ſeek God and Chriſt.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 2. <hi>How, or after what manner we muſt ſeek
them.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Where we may ſeek after <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> We may find them in the <hi>works of
Creation;</hi> theſe will repreſent <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> unto
us, the Power and Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> by whom the
World was made; <pb facs="tcp:33666:19"/>
               <hi>In omnire aspectabili quaedam extant
veſtigia Dei;</hi> In all the <hi>viſible creatures,</hi> there be ſome
prints of the <hi>inviſible God;</hi> ſo that he which lives altogether
without <hi>God,</hi> muſt needs be
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without excuſe, having
<hi>God</hi> ſo near to him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> We may find them <hi>in the Word,</hi> 2
<hi>Cor.</hi> 4.6. The glory of <hi>God</hi> ſhines there in the face of
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and to them that are converſant in the Word,
<hi>God</hi> hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to reveal himſelf, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.2. <hi>To
this man will I look, even to him that is poor, and of a contrite spirit, and
trembleth at my word.</hi> And the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> gives this direction,
<hi>Rom.</hi> 10.6.7. <hi>Say not in thine heart, who ſhall aſcend into
Heaven? that is to bring Chriſt down from above; or, who ſhall deſcend
into the deep? that is to bring up Chriſt again from the dead. But what
ſaith it? The word is night thee, even in the mouth, and in thy heart; that
is, the word of faith which we preach.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> We may find them <hi>in Prayer, Jam.</hi> 4.8.
<hi>Draw night to God, and he will draw nigh to you.</hi> If you will be
ſtrangers to the duty of Prayer, <hi>to the Throne of Grace, God</hi> will be
a ſtranger to you; he hath promiſed to draw nigh to them, that draw nigh to
him; and ſo in <hi>Exod.</hi> 20.24. <hi>In all places where I record my
Name, I will come unto thee, and I will bleſſe thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> We may find them <hi>in our Communion with the
People of God. Where two or three are met together in my Name, there will I
be</hi> (ſaies <hi>Chriſt</hi>) <hi>in the midſt of them.</hi> Therefore
<hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> directs us to go up by the foot-ſteps of the Flock;
and they enquire wiſely, <hi>Cant.</hi> 6.1. that ſay to the
<hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt, Whither is thy beloved gone, that we may
ſeek him with thee?</hi> and when the two <hi>Diſciples</hi> went to
<hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maus,</hi> communing of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> He came and joyned himſelf
with them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, How, or after what manner we muſt ſeek</hi> God
<hi>and</hi> Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Take theſe four following <hi>Directions.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Affect your ſelves with the worth and excellency of
this preſence of</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt; carry a high eſteem of
them in your hearts; think with your ſelves, how ſafely they are
<hi>Immured;</hi> how <hi>Encaſtled</hi> and <hi>Provided</hi> for, who have
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with them; as the <hi>Prophet</hi> ſaid to
his ſervant, <pb facs="tcp:33666:19"/>
               <hi>There is more for them, than can be againſt
them,</hi> Iſai. 33.16. <hi>their place of defence, is the Munition of
Rocks,</hi> &amp;c. O what ſweetneſs and ſatisfaction have they within,
with whom <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> abides<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as the <hi>Spouſe</hi> doth expreſs
it, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Becauſe of the ſavour of thy good Ointments,
thy Name is as Ointment poured forth, therefore do the Virgins love thee.</hi>
Thy Name of <hi>Mercy, Wiſdom,</hi> and <hi>Faithfulneſſe;</hi> how doth
this refreſh their hearts, that have the preſence of <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt?</hi> O ſweetneſs and ſatisfaction beyond expreſſion!
and then conclude, <hi>Sitantus; quarentibus
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> quantus
poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentibus;</hi> If he be ſo good to them that <hi>ſeek him,</hi>
how good is he to them that <hi>enjoy him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Labour to affect your ſouls with the great want
and need that you have of the preſence of</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt;
while men think in their hearts, they can be well enough without <hi>God</hi>
and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> they will never ſeek after them, but ſay, as in
<hi>Jer.</hi> 2.31. <hi>We are Lords, we will come no more un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee,
(i.)</hi> We have ſtrength enough of our own, we need no more of thy
ſupport; and thus <hi>David</hi> brings in the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, priding themſelves,
in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 10.4. <hi>The wicked through the pride of his
countenance</hi> (as in the original, <hi>through the pride of his Noſe</hi>)
<hi>will not ſeek after God. God</hi> is not in all his thoughts, when
theſe proud <hi>Laodician Spirits</hi> will not <hi>ſock,</hi> the poor,
hungry, deſolate ſoul, that ſees a need of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,
find</hi> them.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Quicken your ſelves to much diligence in
ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing:</hi> The <hi>Prophet</hi> complains, <hi>No man ſtirreth up
himſelf to ſeek the Lord.</hi> It is a buſineſſe of <hi>the
greateſt concernment,</hi> and moſt not be attended <hi>with a cold
indifferency,</hi> but as one ſet on by a true love, and where that is,
<hi>Non quie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, ſed quer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Love will he
reſtleſſ in the pur<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap> of the
thing, or perſon beloved. See with what heat men ſeek the world, with much
more heat ſeek <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt.</hi> We muſt do as the woman
that had loſt her <hi>Groat;</hi> ſhe lights a Candle, ſweeps the
Houſe, ſeeks diligently; ſo we muſt ſet up the <hi>light of the
Word,</hi> and to work with the <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a ſerious repentance,</hi> and <hi>thorough
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>ation,</hi> and <hi>diligently
enquir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Thus <hi>David</hi>
with a very vigilant eye, ſeeks him whom his ſoul loved, <hi>Pſal.</hi>
130.4.5. <hi>I will not give reſt to mine eyes, nor ſlumber to my eye lids,
till I have found out a pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> for
God,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:20"/>Laſtly, <hi>Reſolve with your ſelves never to
give over, till you come to the perfect and full enjoyment of them;</hi> As
<hi>Job</hi> ſaid, <hi>I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> all
the dayes of my appointed time.</hi> So do you ſeek all the days of your
appointed time. If we would find <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> we muſt
ſeek all the dayes of our lives. They that will <hi>find</hi> what they
<hi>ſeek,</hi> muſt <hi>ſeek</hi> till they <hi>find;</hi> As
<hi>God</hi> in the <hi>Creation,</hi> did not reſt till he had made
<hi>Man,</hi> ſo <hi>Man</hi> ſhould not reſt till he hath found
<hi>God;</hi> And as in the <hi>Redemption, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> did never
ceaſe ſeeking, till he had found all the <hi>loſt ſheep of the Houſe
of Iſrael;</hi> ſo we ſhould never give o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, till we have made
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> our own.</p>
            <p>This ſhould be the work of our lives, <hi>and upon this work I
muſt leave you.</hi>
            </p>
            <q> 
               <p> 
                  <hi>For now I muſt tell you,</hi> That <hi>(perhaps)</hi> you
may not ſee my face, or bear my voice any more in this place; yet not out of
any peeviſh humour, or diſaffection to the preſent Authority of the
Kingdom (I call <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man</hi> to witneſs this day) it being
my own <hi>Practice</hi> and <hi>Counſel</hi> to you all, <hi>To Fear GOD,
and Honour the KING;</hi> but rather a real diſatisfaction in ſome
particulars impoſed, to which, (not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all endeavours to that
purpoſe) my conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence cannot yet be eſpouſed. <hi>Wherefore,</hi> I
hope, in this, and in all my abode with you, I may ſay <hi>(without
oſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on)</hi> with the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> in the 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.12.
<hi>Our rejoycing is this, The teſtimony of a good Conſcience, that in
ſimplicity, and godly ſincerity, we have had our converſation in the
world, eſpecially to you words;</hi> And as he ſaid in <hi>Acts</hi>
20.26.27. So, <hi>I take you to record this day, that I have endeavoured to be
pure from the blood of all men; for I have not ſhunned to declare to you, the
whole counſel of God,</hi> both by my <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Doctrine;</hi>
becauſe <hi>I</hi> knew this very well, that (as one ſayes,) <hi>S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap> loqu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                        <desc>•…</desc>
                     </gap>is
vita, non oratia;</hi> that the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers life, is the moſt lively
preaching.</p> 
               <p> I ſhall only adde this <hi>(my Friends)</hi> That though my
lips be ſealed up, that I may not ſpeak <hi>from God</hi> to you, yet I
ſhall not ceaſe to ſpeak to <hi>God</hi> for you, as ever I have done;
And though I cannot have you in my <hi>eye,</hi> yet I ſhall lodge you in my
<hi>heart;</hi> And asking nothing of you, but your <hi>Prayers,</hi> ſhall
hope to meet you daily at the <hi>Throne</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> and that at
laſt we may enjoy one another in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
               </p> 
               <p> 
                  <pb facs="tcp:33666:20"/>And becauſe they ſay, <hi>The word of a</hi>
Dying man <hi>wake the deepeſt impreſſion,</hi> before I am altogether
<hi>Civilly dead,</hi> I ſhall give you one <hi>Exhortation</hi>
more.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Exh. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let it be your
endeavour to keep <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with you, that they may
make their abode with your hearts and houſes, <hi>that whatever you loſe,
you may not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In the General.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Take heed you do not ſlight or abuſe his
Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Do not Deſpiſe or neglect his
Ordinances.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Be ſure you do not grieve his Spirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, <hi>Obſerve more
particularly theſe ten directions,</hi> which I would leave with you.</p>
            <p>That <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> may make their conſtant
abode with you.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Endeavour to pleaſe</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt,
<hi>and to walk as the Gospel commands,</hi> In all well-pleaſing. <hi>And
for this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, Obſerve theſe three Rules.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Entertain</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>like
themſelves.</hi> Now they are come to you, ſay as <hi>Solomon</hi> did of
his <hi>Temple,</hi> which he had prepared for his <hi>God; The Heaven of
Heavens cannot contain thee, much leſſe, this poor Tent;</hi> ſo, with
the moſt humble frame of ſpirit, <hi>admire his greatneſſe, and
infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite condeſcention, for he is the King of Glory;</hi> as in
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 24. And ſo give him ſuitable entertainment, for <hi>he
will dwell with the humble and contrite ſpirit.</hi> If <hi>Elizabeth</hi>
wonder'd at the viſit which <hi>Mary</hi> gave her, with a <hi>whence is it
that the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of my Lord is come unto me?</hi> then admire that the
<hi>Lord</hi> himſelf ſhould come, not only <hi>to viſit your
hearts,</hi> but <hi>to make ſuch a gracious abode with you;</hi> And as the
<hi>Centurion</hi> ſaid to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the <hi>Goſpel, I am not
worthy that thou ſhouldst come under my Roof.</hi> So acknowledge your
unworthineſſe of ſo rich and unparalleld a grace, that <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt</hi> ſhould come in unto you, to abide with you!</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Wait upon</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>with
all readineſſe of mind, to obſerve every intimation of the Will of</hi>
God; <hi>to you.</hi> Stand alwayes ready, as Servants wait upon the hand of
their Maſter, ſaying in your hearts, <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have me to
do? or, what wilt thou have me to ſuffer?</hi> It is the frame <pb facs="tcp:33666:21"/>and poſture which <hi>Chriſt</hi> commends to his <hi>Diſciples,
Luke</hi> 12.35. <hi>Let your loyns be girded about, and your lights burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
to do his will, as it is done in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>Take pleaſure and delight in the company and
ſocie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt, <hi>above all the pleaſures in
the world.</hi> Do nothing, without firſt calling <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt</hi> into the action. <hi>Remember this in Theſe four caſes
especially.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Pray</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>along with
you into all your ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual duties,</hi> that you may be ſure to perform
them all accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the mind of <hi>God.</hi> None knows better what will
pleaſe <hi>God,</hi> than himſelf; don't enquire ſo much <hi>what others
ſay,</hi> but what <hi>God appoints;</hi> 'tis not what this or that man
ſayes, how we muſt ſerve <hi>God,</hi> but what <hi>God</hi> ſayes
himſelf; as <hi>Aguſtine</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Manichee,</hi> in another
caſe, <hi>Nec egote, nec tu me, ſed ambo audiamus Apoſtolum;</hi> So hear
what <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſay to us, <hi>as to the performance
of all our duties:</hi> If we will entertain <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> and have their compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, we muſt ſet before them ſuch
ſavoury meat as they like, leſt we be like them (<hi>Mat</hi> 15.9.) of
whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſayes, <hi>In vain do they worſhip me,</hi> &amp;c.
and our ſervice be like theirs, of which the <hi>Lord</hi> ſaid, <hi>Who
hath required theſe things at your hands?</hi> O what was that great evil the
people were guilty of, for which there comes that heavy judgement,
<hi>Pſal.</hi> 78.60. <hi>He forſook the Tabernacle of</hi> Shiloh, <hi>the
Tent which he placed among them.</hi> Sure it was ſome great <hi>guilt,</hi>
in the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer verſes we find it to be their <hi>Hypocriſie,
Apoſtacy,</hi> and <hi>Idolatry,</hi> any taint of this kind, will make the
jealous <hi>God</hi> forſake our ſolemn meetings.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Pray God and Chriſt into all your Civil
affairs</hi> The <hi>Greeks</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
with <hi>God</hi> in their entrance upon every work, was a commendable
practiſe. It is reported of <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Scipio</hi> the <hi>Roman,</hi> that
he would alway go firſt to the <hi>Capitol,</hi> and then to the
<hi>Senate;</hi> So we ſhould begin our <hi>Civil Imployments</hi> with
<hi>Spiritual duties;</hi> And do as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> Servant, when he was to
take a wife for his Maſters Son, he took <hi>God</hi> along with him; and
thus <hi>to abide with God,</hi> is to have <hi>God to abide with us.</hi>
Therefore ſayes the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.20 <hi>Let every
man abide in the ſame calling, wherein he was called,</hi> and in the 24
verſe, <hi>Brethren let eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man wherein he is called, therein abide with
God,</hi> And <hi>God</hi> will abide with him.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:33666:21"/>
               <hi>Thirdly, Pray</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt
<hi>to your Tables at your eating and drinking, For man doth not live by bread
onely.</hi> If theſe be <hi>Gueſts</hi> at your <hi>Tables,</hi> you muſt
needs have <hi>Cheer enough;</hi> there's more <hi>ſweetneſſe</hi> in a
<hi>morſel with them, then in all dain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties without them;</hi> And then you
may be ſure alſo, your Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles ſhall not become a Snare unto you.
<hi>Theophraſtus</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports of the <hi>Heathens,</hi> that they did
firſt <gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and then
<gap reason="foreign" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, they did firſt
<hi>Sacrifice</hi> and then <hi>Kill,</hi> lay on their meat, entertain and
eat. And it is the <hi>Apostles</hi> rule, ſeeing all things come of
<hi>God</hi> through <hi>Christ,</hi> That <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi>
ſhould not be <hi>Unbidden Gueſts;</hi> but as in 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.31.
<hi>Whether you eat or drink, or whatſoever ye do, do all to the Glory of
God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly, Pray.</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>along with
you in Morning when you riſe, and at Evening when you lie down;</hi> viſit
him Morning by Morning and Evening by Evening; this is the way to have a
<hi>Proſperous day,</hi> and a <hi>Safe night; David</hi> took this courſe,
<hi>Pſal</hi> 4.8. <hi>I will both lay me down, and take my reſt, for thou
Lord, only makeſt me dwell in ſafety;</hi> and this gave <hi>Jacob</hi>
ſuch a pleaſant Dream, <hi>Gen.</hi> 28. that having <hi>God</hi> with him,
he was an night within view of <hi>Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>2</label> 
               <hi>Secondly, Love</hi> God
<hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>above all, and then</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt
<hi>will not depart from you;</hi> For <hi>He ſhews mercy to Thouſands of
them that love him,</hi> and hath made over <hi>Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,</hi> and
<hi>Heaven,</hi> and <hi>All,</hi> to them that <hi>love</hi> him. It is
re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported of <hi>Ignatius,</hi> that his Love was ſuch to <hi>God</hi> and
<hi>Chriſt,</hi> that he had the name of <hi>Chriſt, Cordi ej<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>s inſc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap>iptum;</hi> Graven upon his heart. It is ſuch a
<hi>Heart-love</hi> that <hi>He</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires; for <hi>He is a jealous
God,</hi> and will have all our Love.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>If we Love any thing better;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> It will ſteal away our <hi>Hearts</hi> from
<hi>God;</hi> And</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It will take off the <hi>Heart</hi> of
<hi>God</hi> from us; ſo that <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> will ſet
themſelves againſt us.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>3</label> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> If we would have
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> to make their conſtant abode with us,
<hi>Delight in the Society and Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of the People of</hi> God,
<hi>with whom they dwell;</hi> Never be aſhamed to converſe with them, whom
<hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> do own for theirs. The <hi>Apoſtles</hi>
argument why we ſhould en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain <hi>Strangers,</hi> in <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.2.
<hi>(becauſe thereby ſome have entertained Angels unawares) is but mean and
inconſiderable to <pb facs="tcp:33666:22"/>this Reaſon,</hi> why we ſhould entertain
and own the <hi>Saints of God;</hi> for thereby we are ſure to <hi>entertain
Chriſt;</hi> as in <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.40. For this cauſe the
<hi>Gibeonites</hi> made a <hi>League</hi> with <hi>Iſrael; For we have heard
that God is with you.</hi> And there is a promiſe in <hi>Zech.</hi> 8.23.
That <hi>Ten men out of all Languages ſhall take hold of the ſkirt of a
Jew, ſaying, we will go with you, for we have heard that God is with
you,</hi> Mal. 3.16. <hi>They that feared the Lord, ſpake often one to
another, and the Lord hearkned, and heard it,</hi> &amp;c. He was with them,
and indeed, <hi>God dwells in the Tabernacles of the Righteous.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>4</label> 
               <hi>Fourthly, If we would have the
conſtant abode of</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>with us, Let us keep our
ſelves clean from Sin, our Hearts pure, Conſciences undefiled,</hi> and as
the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſayes, <hi>voyd of Offence towards God, and towards
Men,</hi> very <hi>careful</hi> not to <hi>Sin</hi> againſt <hi>God;</hi> and
very <hi>circumſpect</hi> not to <hi>Sin</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Man;</hi> that
this may be our Comfort, that the world muſt needs ſay of us, as they did
of <hi>Daniel,</hi> that <hi>they could find nothing againſt him; ſave in
the Law of his God,</hi> as in <hi>Daniel</hi> 6.5. Whatever others
<hi>doe,</hi> beware of <hi>Sin.</hi> Say as <hi>Joſhuah, I and my Houſe
will ſerve the Lord.</hi> Watch againſt <hi>Sin; Chuſe any</hi>
Suffering, <hi>rather then the leaſt</hi> Sin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Conſider in that choice two particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider <hi>in all your ſufferings, God
will be with you, but in any of your Sins, he will not abode with you;</hi> as
in the example of <hi>Iſrael, Exod.</hi> 32.23. <hi>When the</hi> Calf
<hi>was got into the</hi> Camp, God <hi>forſakes the</hi> Hoaſt <hi>of</hi>
Iſrael; <hi>When Saul</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſook the <hi>Lord,</hi> the <hi>Spirit</hi>
of the <hi>Lord</hi> forſook <hi>him.</hi> That was an excellent Saying of
<hi>Azariah</hi> the Son of <hi>Obed,</hi> in the 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 15.2. and
Oh that all <hi>England</hi> could hear it! <hi>Hear thou me Aſa, and all
Judah, The Lord is with you, while you be with him; If you ſeek him, he will
be found of you; but if ye forſake him, he will forſake you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, <hi>'Tis an Act of high
preſumption, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flecting much upon the Purity and Holyneſſe of God, for
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to imagine that</hi> God
<hi>will own, and proſper them with his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, while they go on to do
wickedly, in their</hi> Whoredomes, Drunkeneſſe, Blaſphemy, <hi>and all
manner of</hi> Prophaneſſe; which <hi>God</hi> can no more <hi>own,</hi>
then <hi>diſown</hi> himſelf. So they fooliſhly promiſed themſelves
<hi>Peace, Deut.</hi> 29.19. <hi>though they walk in the imagination of their
Hearts, and add Drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <pb facs="tcp:33666:22"/>to Thirſt;</hi> But the
<hi>Lord</hi> will not <hi>ſpare,</hi> but his <hi>Anger</hi> and
<hi>Jealouſie</hi> ſhall <hi>ſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ak</hi> againſt <hi>them,</hi> till he hath brought them down from
their high Mount of a <hi>Sinful</hi> and <hi>Carnal Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</hi>
Therefore the <hi>Prophet</hi> reproves that wicked people, <hi>Mich.</hi>
3.11. where the <hi>Judges,</hi> the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and the
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets</hi> were corrupted. Yet they ſay, <hi>Is not the Lord among
us, none evil can come upon us, Therefore ſhall Zion be plowed as a
Field,</hi> &amp;c. as <hi>Abner</hi> ſaid to <hi>Joab, This will prove an
evil thing, and a bitter in the latter end;</hi> as <hi>Galen</hi> ſayes of
Meats, <hi>Quae dulcia ſunt facile in bilem &amp; amaritudinem
convertun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur;</hi> Sweet meats generate Choller and Corrupt matter; So
<hi>Sin</hi> that is a <hi>ſweet morſel</hi> now, will be <hi>Shame, Death,
and Hell</hi> at laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>5</label> 
               <hi>Fifthly, With an humble
acknowledgment of former Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renneſſe, under Gods gracious preſence with
you, reſolve and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to be more fruitful. God</hi> never left his
<hi>Vineyard,</hi> and pull'd up the Hedge, and commanded the Rain not to fall
upon it, in <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5. <hi>till it became Barren, or did bear cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
fruit.</hi> The exil'd Confeſſors in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes,
confeſſed that (as <hi>Urſin</hi> ſayes in the Preface to his
<hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme</hi>) the cauſe of their preſent ſuffering, was their
for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer <hi>Barrenneſſe</hi> and <hi>Unprofitableneſſe</hi> under the
<hi>Goſpel;</hi> and a ſad example of this is <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> over
whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> laments. <hi>O Jeruſalem, Jeruſalem, thou,</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>if thou hadſt known in this thy day,</hi> &amp;c. but now they
<hi>are hid from thine eyes;</hi> and when once a people grow up to this
heighth to reject the <hi>Goſpel,</hi> then expect ſome fearful
<hi>Judgement.</hi> Read the laſt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of <hi>Chronicles,</hi> the Second
Book, and at the 16 <hi>verſe,</hi> and then you will ſee, when the wrath
of <hi>God</hi> is like to break out upon a People without a remedy.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>6</label> 
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> If you would
have the continual abode of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with you;
<hi>Let God have all your Thoughts,</hi> let <hi>Him be your meditation;</hi>
this is the way to have the beſt <hi>Company</hi> when you be alone;
<hi>David</hi> would meditate of him day and night, and profeſſed <hi>the
meditation of him, ſhould be ſweet to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Here conſider two particulars.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Conſider, <hi>that no Place, State, or
Condition, can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Soul of this way of ſecret Communion with God and
Christ;</hi> This priviledge could not be denyed to a <hi>benighted 
<pb facs="tcp:33666:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>Jacob,</hi> to an <hi>Impriſoned Jeremiah,</hi> to an
<hi>Exil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d</hi> John <hi>in
Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mos;</hi> by this (ſaies <hi>Jerom</hi>) <hi>Solitudo fit
Paradiſas,</hi> a man may turn a <hi>Wilderneſs</hi> into a
<hi>Paradiſe;</hi> and therefore we read in <hi>Cant.</hi> 11.12. how the
<hi>Spouſe</hi> invites <hi>Chriſt</hi> to go with her, as <hi>Iſaac</hi>
did into the <hi>Fields</hi> to meditate, <hi>Come let's go into the Fields,
and lodge in the Villages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, <hi>In theſe ſecret ſilent
viſits of the Soul,</hi> God <hi>and</hi> Chriſt <hi>do take abundance of
delight;</hi> Our <hi>Night thoughts,</hi> our <hi>Field thoughts,</hi> our
<hi>Cloſet thoughts.</hi> are very <hi>welcom</hi> to <hi>Them;</hi> yea,
when we can do no more but think of <hi>God,</hi> our very <hi>thoughts</hi>
ſhall be an <hi>accepted ſervice,</hi> Cant. 2.13. <hi>He loveth the
Fig-tree, that putteth forth her green Figs.</hi> The ripe fruit is in the
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                  <desc>•…</desc>
               </gap>d; ſo <hi>holy endeavours</hi>
in <hi>pure breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> and <hi>deſires, God accepts,</hi> when our
<hi>Infirmity,</hi> or the <hi>Iniquity</hi> of the <hi>Times</hi> may be
ſuch, that we can do no more.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Direct. </seg>7</label> 
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> If we will
have <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> to make their conſtant abode with us,
<hi>then let us walk humbly with God. He that beholds the proud afar off, will
be nigh to them that humble their ſouls under his mighty hand,</hi> Iſa.
57.15. <hi>Thus ſaies the high and lofty one, that inhabits Eternity, whoſe
Name is Holy; I dwell in the High and Holy place, with him alſo, that is of
an humble and contrite ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>God</hi> hath two <hi>Heavens</hi> in which he dwells.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, His Glory</hi> dwells in the high and holy place, in
<hi>Heaven</hi> above.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, His Grace</hi> dwells in the humble and lowly
ſpirit. <hi>Here will I dwell, ſaies God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>8</label> 
               <hi>Eighthly,</hi> If you would
have the conſtant abode of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi> with you,
<hi>be ſure to look to your hearts, that you walk in your uprightneſs; be
true to the Word of God, be true to your profeſſion.</hi> There is not in
the world a more lively repreſentation and Image of <hi>God,</hi> than the
<hi>heart</hi> of the <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right;</hi> therefore <hi>God</hi> loves ſo
much, when he hath drawn his likeneſs upon them to walk with them; therefore
<hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> reſolves, <hi>Pſal</hi> 101.2. <hi>I will walk in the
midſt of mine houſe with a perfect heart; O when wilt thou come unto
me?</hi> This was the comfort of the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> that in
<hi>ſimplicity,</hi> and <hi>godly ſincerity,</hi> he had his
<hi>converſation</hi> in the world; <hi>God</hi> will be with
<hi>ſuch,</hi> and <hi>ſuch</hi> ſhall be with <hi>God, Pſal.</hi>
37.37. <hi>Mark the perfect man, behold the upright, the end of that man 
<pb facs="tcp:33666:23"/>is peace;</hi> And thus <hi>God</hi> appointed <hi>Abraham</hi> to
walk, that he might be with him <hi>a God in Covenant, Gen</hi> 17. <hi>Walk
before me, be thou perfect;</hi> and gives him this encouragement, <hi>I am God
All-ſufficient: Gods All ſufficiency</hi> being ſufficient to keep the
<hi>Soul</hi> upright, being rightly improved.</p>
            <p>There be <hi>two things</hi> which uſually <hi>Bias</hi> the
<hi>Soul</hi> away from <hi>God,</hi> and makes it warp from its holy
principles, 1. <hi>The Frowns.</hi> 2. <hi>The Flatteries</hi> of the
world.</p>
            <p>Againſt both which, there is a ſufficient remedy in the
<hi>All-ſufficient God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That which often perverts the Soul from the
truth, is the <hi>fear of troubles and wants;</hi> If I keep my integrity,
(ſaies the Soul) I ſhall be <hi>Undone,</hi> I ſhall <hi>Loſe my
eſtate, Embroyl</hi> my ſelf in many <hi>Troubles;</hi> perhaps a
<hi>Priſon, Exile,</hi> or <hi>Death</hi> comes next. But what force is there
in this Tentation? If we hear on the other hand, <hi>God</hi> ſaying, if thou
wilt be <hi>up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right,</hi> fear no troubles, no wants, <hi>I am a God
All-ſufficient,</hi> as in <hi>Job</hi> 22.25. to the end of the Chapter,
<hi>The Almighty ſhall be thy defence</hi> (then fear no force) <hi>thou
ſhalt have plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Silver, thou ſhalt gather Gold as duſt, and the
Gold of Ophir, as the ſtones of the Brooks,</hi> Then fear no wants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> There is another thing in the world that hath a
very great influence upon the ſpirit of a man, to pervert him, and turn him
from his integrity; and that is <hi>The hopes of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, and greatneſs
of the world;</hi> But this is but a poor bait, if we look upon the
<hi>All-ſufficiency</hi> of <hi>God:</hi> Doth the <hi>World</hi> promiſe
thee <hi>Riches? God</hi> will out-bid the world, and gives <hi>Eternal
Riches.</hi> Will the <hi>World</hi> give <hi>Pleaſures? God</hi> will give
<hi>better; with him is fulneſs of joy, and pleaſures for evermore.</hi>
Will the <hi>World</hi> give <hi>Gold? God</hi> will give <hi>Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds.</hi>
Will the <hi>World</hi> give all its <hi>Glory? God</hi> will give thee the
<hi>Glory</hi> of a <hi>better World,</hi> rather than that ſhall be a
ſnare unto thee.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>9</label> 
               <hi>Ninthly, Pray much, pray
continually; God</hi> will be in the <hi>hearts</hi> and <hi>houſes</hi> of
his <hi>Praying people,</hi> when he hath a <hi>Curſe</hi> in ſtore for
<hi>Prayerleſs Families,</hi> in <hi>Jerem.</hi> 10. the laſt
<hi>verſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>That God will abide with</hi> you, <hi>and the</hi>
Kingdom <hi>in his</hi> Goſpel, <hi>and pure</hi> Ordinances; that you may
dwell in <hi>Beth-el,</hi> and not in <hi>Berl-aven,</hi> a houſe of vanity
and grief. Pray that <hi>God</hi> will not remove his <hi>Candleſtick</hi>
from <hi>you,</hi> nor <pb facs="tcp:33666:24"/>utterly extinguiſh the light of the
<hi>Kingdom.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Pray, and I ſhall pray with you, <hi>that God
will give you a faithful Paſtour after his own heart,</hi> not according to
your <hi>hearts,</hi> that he may teach you by his <hi>Doctrine</hi> and his
<hi>Life</hi> too; A faithful Teacher, to go <hi>in,</hi> and <hi>out</hi>
before you; to ſhew you the <hi>Word</hi> of the <hi>Lord;</hi> One that may
be among you, as it was ſaid of <hi>Athanaſius,</hi> that he was <hi>Magnes
&amp; Adamas.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Magnes, As a Load-ſtone,</hi> to draw your Souls
with a <hi>gentle hand,</hi> and <hi>melting heart,</hi> from your ſins
<hi>Heaven-ward.</hi>
               </item>
               <item> 2. <hi>Adamas, As an Adamant,</hi> of an invincible courage
and zeal againſt all ſin and prophaneſs; one that will not ſpare
<hi>Sin.</hi> That he may ſave your <hi>Souls.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Pray</hi> that <hi>God</hi> would give you a <hi>Star,</hi> a
<hi>Star</hi> out of his <hi>right hand,</hi> not a <hi>Churliſh Orion,</hi>
that brings a Cold, Barren, and Cloudy <hi>Winter.</hi> but a
<hi>Benevolent</hi> and <hi>Friendly Pleiades,</hi> that there may be many Sons
brought into <hi>God,</hi> and your <hi>Souls</hi> may find a continual
<hi>Spring,</hi> and that <hi>you</hi> may be as <hi>Trees</hi> of
<hi>Gods</hi> own planting, <hi>and may flouriſh in the Courts of the houſe
of our God, and may bring forth more fruit in old age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Dir. </seg>10</label> 
               <hi>Tenthly,</hi> and Laſtly,
If you would have the conſtant abode of <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Chriſt</hi>
with you, <hi>Conform, Conform univerſally, and fully to the Goſpel of
Chriſt, Conſent and Aſſent Unfeignedly, to all the Truths and Doctrines
thereof,</hi> that you may walk wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of <hi>God,</hi> and all that
<hi>Grace</hi> which hath been revealed to you: for <hi>Chriſt</hi> hath
ſaid, <hi>If a man keep his Word, the Father will love him,</hi> and both
Father and Son, <hi>will come to him, and make their abode with him.</hi>
Wherefore I ſhall conclude this <hi>Exhortation</hi> with that of the
<hi>Apostle,</hi> in <hi>Philippians</hi> 1.2.7. <hi>Only Let your
converſation be ſuch as becometh the Goſpel of Chriſt, that whether I
come and ſee you, or elſe be abſent from you, I may hear of your affairs,
that ye ſtand faſt in one ſpirit, with one mind, ſtriving together for
the faith of the Gospel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſo ſhut up all with that in <hi>Acts</hi> 20.32.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And now Brethren, I commend you to God, and to the Word of his
Grace, which is able to build you up, and to give you an Inheritance among all
them which are Sanctified.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:33666:24"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
